<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the schism of England. Wherein particularly Mr. Hales and Mr. Hobbs are modestly accosted. / By Philip Scot. Permissu superiorum.</title>
            <author>Scot, Philip.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 143 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1395_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2593</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872105</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124528</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94272)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124528)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 255:E1395[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the schism of England. Wherein particularly Mr. Hales and Mr. Hobbs are modestly accosted. / By Philip Scot. Permissu superiorum.</title>
                  <author>Scot, Philip.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 273, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Amsterdam [i.e. London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed anno Dom. 1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the second and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Errata leaf immediately follows text.</note>
                  <note>Thomason copy imperfect; frequent show-through.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 5th 1650."; Amsterdam has been crossed out and replaced with "London".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hales, John, 1584-1656 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hobbes, Thomas, 1588-1679 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Schism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:124528:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF THE SCHISM OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mr.</hi> HALES <hi>and Mr.</hi> HOBBS <hi>are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly accoſted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> PHILIP SCOT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Permiſſu Superiorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AMSTERDAM</hi> Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1650</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:124528:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:124528:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Author Supervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving intended to both the Univerſities, as a Theam to be diſcuſſed in their next Scholaſtick Olimpicks.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> was asked who was a good Orator,
<pb facs="tcp:124528:3"/>he ſaid he would give the ſame anſwer, which the Stoicks would give if this queſtion were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Zeno, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anthes,</hi> or <hi>Chriſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> whom they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed great and worthy men; but not ſuch as had obtained the height of which human nature is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:124528:3"/>
            <p>The ſame I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs of you, ye have made large progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the ſchool of wiſdom, and many of you have almoſt reached the topp of human capacity, but yet ye have not obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned pure wiſdom: And truly, I fear as the old Platoniſts confeſsed of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yee will never
<pb facs="tcp:124528:4"/>reach it till your ſouls final ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: when ſhe will to her loſs finde where ſhe miſt her footing, except yee would (which were a noble deſign) maugre the injuries of the time and place where ye live, life up your eyes, and conclude with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pictetus <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our aim ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:124528:4"/>be to ſeek God with a pure Soul. This can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done unleſs without any limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ye ſubmit to theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to thoſe commanding Oracles (as the Ancients call them) which God by his holy Spouſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth to our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; to this end it is firſt neceſſary to know which is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:124528:5"/>Church, whence all wiſdom as from a pure ſource flowes: to this the enſuing diſcourſe will inable the Reader.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Witten by your Servant PHILIP SCOT</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124528:5"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF THE <hi>Schiſm of England.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Church of Rome taken in the latitude of her Communion is God's onely Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His titular Theſis will ſeem a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox, by reaſon of the ſtrong pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice our Country is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:124528:6"/>with againſt an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent truth: but the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding diſcourſe will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate by lineary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction the moſt aſſured certainty of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paucis opus eſt ad bonam mentem litteris;</hi> Sen. ep. 106.</p>
               <p>I ſhall be brief; yet I hope ſufficiently large, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as <hi>St. Cyprian,</hi> tract. 3. <hi>de ſimplicitate Prelatorum. Tractatu longò atque argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis non eſt opus. Probatio eſt ad fidem facilis compendio veritatis.</hi> Our holy faith needs no tedious proofs, but onely compendious declarations. That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> did hold, and openly profeſs the true faith of Chriſt in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:124528:6"/>Apoſtles time, <hi>St. Paul Rom.</hi> 1.8. is an abundant wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: That alſo the other Churches through the world did in faith commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with her, is there manifeſt; and that ſhe kept the ſame faith ſure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched, for the firſt ſix hundred years from Chriſt to <hi>Gregory</hi> the great; not onely the learnedſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants for the moſt part confeſs, but by this, even to the blind is apparent, that all Councels aſſembled in thoſe times, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the firſt four general ones; as is moſt evident in the Acts or actions (as they call them) of each Councel agreed in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:124528:7"/>ſame profeſſion of faith, held very ſtrict communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation againſt all hereſies; as in the condemnation of <hi>Arrius</hi> in the Nicen; of <hi>Macedonius</hi> in the firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinopolitan; of <hi>Neſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in the firſt Epheſian; of <hi>Eutiches,</hi> and <hi>Dioſtorus</hi> in the Chalcedon Councels: So that thus far we are ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the integrity of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that is, till <hi>St. Leo</hi> the Pope who was contemporary with the Chalcedon: whence is concluded alſo that all Churches then diſperſed through the whole world; and their Doctors (except ſuch as have been branded with ſome hereſie or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:124528:7"/>did alwayes commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate in faith with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named general Councels witneſſed the faith of all Churches; therefore if the erred, it is neceſſary that all the other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches erred alſo, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that Chriſt had no true Church upon earth. He who deſires to look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe things in a moſt compendious way, let him onely read the Epiſtles of <hi>S. Leo,</hi> and the Regiſter of <hi>St. Gregory,</hi> and there he ſhall ſee moſt evidently, as in a mirrour the connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and agreeing of things together with the former and ſucceeding ages. I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:124528:8"/>ſpeak to thoſe that know the Law, therefore to have given but a hint is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Gregory</hi> the great (who is not noted to have innovated any thing in the faith which he received from his Anceſtors, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of <hi>St. Leo;</hi> who, as we declared was contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary to Chalcedon, and held by all the world in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire in his faith) this needs no other proof then the confeſſion of the Greeks, who alwayes reverenced him and intitled him a Saint, and therefore num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred him among the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; as appeareth even by the Schiſmatick Greeks
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124528:8"/>in the diſpute of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the Councel of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; St. Damaſene,</hi> who was contemporary to <hi>St. Bede,</hi> and a little above one hundred years after <hi>St. Gregory</hi> gives ſo much cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to his writings, that he confeſſeth all the Eaſt and Weſt to adhere to them, even in ſome ſmaller things which are not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally received amongſt us; whence it is moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that he was Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally eſteemed a follower of his, and their forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in faith.</p>
               <p>To bring this evidence more home, we will ſtay in the 4 firſt general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels: They did before ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:124528:9"/>us of the integrity of the Roman Church, and they will do as much for <hi>St. Gregory,</hi> for no man is ignorant that he taught all the world to reverence their faith, next to the four Evangeliſts, whence is concluded, that he was of the ſame faith with them; now <hi>St. Gregory</hi> ſent over the ſame faith to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> then involved with the darkneſs of infidelity by <hi>St. Auſtin</hi> the Monk, and other holy and learned men, who devoutly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, and conſtantly and faithfully kept it until the revolt of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth. But that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith which we recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:124528:9"/>from <hi>St. Gregory</hi> by <hi>St. Auſtin</hi> may to every body appear to be the ſame, which not onely the weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erne, but the Eaſterne Church did profeſs; that is, what the whole univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church did profeſs, beſides what I have ſaid before, it is demonſtrable by the Epiſtles of <hi>St. Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> directed to the Eaſt, in which he ſignifieth that <hi>England</hi> was converted to the faith of <hi>Rome,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears more particularly in his thirtieth Epiſtle, which is to <hi>Eulogius</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal congratulatories received from them, for ſo great a gain of ſouls <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:124528:10"/>whence it followeth mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly, that the Greeks and the Eaſt were of the ſame communion of faith with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there had been no mutual entercourſe of congratulatory letters in things of this nature; this is clearer then can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted. Moreover that <hi>England</hi> never erred from the faith firſt received, or left in any thing that faith, is manifeſt even to chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren if they cannot read; in looking upon the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures in glaſs-windows &amp; graves, in ſeeing the altars ſtill in ſome places extant, in ſeeing the very Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Monaſteries, old Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitals
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:124528:10"/>and Colledges, with the old forms of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Statutes, which without book are conveyed from hand to hand, as in faſting, keeping ſuch and ſuch holy daies in memory of certain mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles obtained by invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of particular Saints, Annual obſequies and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn prayers for the dead benefactors, inſtitution of certain Maſſes to that and ſuch other ends: if they can read, in running over the Chronicles and Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our country, where you ſhall obſerve a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant memory of all theſe old truths, but not any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation or change of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:124528:11"/>faith was ever noted by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Hiſtoriographer for ſo many ages together; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that our country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Gulielmus Neubrigenſis</hi> in his Hiſtory. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, that neither <hi>Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme</hi> nor any other hereſy could faſten upon <hi>England,</hi> though <hi>in alijs mundi parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus tot plluluaverint haereſes</hi> all other parts of the world had been infected with them. A great teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony written by ſo know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man in point eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of our Hiſtories: And <hi>Wicklef's</hi> caſe confirms all, for he got grounds a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand miles hence, as in Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, but here was decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before he was well
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:124528:11"/>born: or what is more brief, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> retained her pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive communion as well with the Roman, as with all other Churches diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed throughout the world (except thoſe which for hereſie or ſchiſm, were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Councels) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our own Hiſtories, no Councel, no Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory ever impoſed the contrary upon our nation; yea it appears by all monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, holy and profane, that <hi>England</hi> did poſitively and clearly communicate with all other, or what is all one, that <hi>England</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved her primitive faith untouched: and that was,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:124528:12"/>as is ſhewed before, the Catholick faith, or the faith of the Catholick Church: therefore <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> till <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth was a member of the true Church of Chriſt; from which he revolting, made her Schiſmatical. All this is witneſſed by <hi>Ball</hi> in his Catalogue, and <hi>Dr. Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fries</hi> Jeſuitiſmes <hi>p.</hi> 2. and <hi>B. Uſher</hi> in his tract of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, whereunto an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity of Proteſtant wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters agree.</p>
               <p>Some will ſay, as of late a Proteſtant Doctor did; that <hi>England</hi> was not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noted in this, becauſe there was none to note her beſides her own in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124528:12"/>Weſt; but it appears, that invocation of Saints and many other doctrines were brought in as a matter of faith againſt the ancients: that is to ſay, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> did bring in thoſe innovations in the Councel of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer: Firſt, that the Doctor did not well obſerve into what a precipice this would caſt him; for if there were no known profeſſions of Chriſt but ſuch who were ours, it's evident that then the Roman Communion was the onely Church of God, even then when it was in his judgment at the worſt, or elſe there was no
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:124528:13"/>Church: This many of their greateſt men have acknowledged; as <hi>Perkins</hi> ſaith, that for many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years this Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had poſſeſſed the whole world; <hi>Napier</hi> upon the Revelations, that for a thouſand years Popery had over-ſwayed the world; to the ſame tenure many more of them ſpeak: All which concludes what I ſaid.</p>
               <p>I anſwer ſecondly: That the firſt and pureſt times of the Church taught the ſame Truths, as almoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of them is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by thoſe of <hi>Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge</hi> in the fourth Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dedicated to Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth;</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:124528:13"/>where they give us a liſt of Juſtification by works, merits, Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal confeſſion, Tradition, Invocation of Saints, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the propitiatory ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſs, miracles obtained at the reliques of Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny had from Proteſtants; that is, from a body of the moſt learned Proteſtants, who joyntly had ſtudied and examined <hi>ex profeſſo</hi> the differences betwixt us, were enough alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Daneus,</hi> in his tract of the Church, a very fierce Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, dividing the whole time ſince Chriſt into ages, giving to the Apoſtles the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:124528:14"/>firſt age, ſpecifies that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then virginity was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced as more worthy then marriage. The <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of the body and blood of Chriſt; and there was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence uſed to the very ſymbols <hi>Parum importune;</hi> a great deal to ſoon <hi>Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onum indigeſta moles,</hi> whole heaps of Traditions were unwiſely brought in; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Church mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with anointing them, which was alſo uſed in baptiſm, extream unction, and the like, Biſhops, <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matus eccleſiae Romanae neſcio qua credulitate in coelum ſubla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt.</hi> The Roman ſeats Supremacy, I know not by what eaſie belief, was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:124528:14"/>even then cryed up to the very heavens, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan <hi>myſterium iniquitatis</hi> the great myſtery of iniquity.</p>
               <p>A fair confeſſion; and in the next age he is more prodigal, but here is enough for any ingenious man; if you would alſo read him upon <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> his tract of hereſies, how he inverts the judgement of the old Church, and will have thoſe doctrines which then were eſteemed hereſies, to be true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines; and in this he ſhews how Proteſtants are conſtrained to turn the Church upſide down, which is indeed true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancy to make all old
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:124528:15"/>and firſt Chriſtians here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques with us. To whom our country-man <hi>Perkins</hi> in his Problems agreeth, bewayling that Gods Church above thirteen hundred years ago was polluted and overſpread with theſe errors. <hi>Uſher</hi> in his latine book of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which in the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſpiece promiſeth a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction from the Apoſtles downward; in the book it ſelf he doth not once make any reall pretence to it, as if he had wholly forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten what was promiſed in the title; he turns himſelf to diſcover where there is the leaſt ſhadow, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:124528:15"/>of our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as if he gloried to ſee their nakedneſs, which Chriſtian Charity and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty would cover; but to ſhew the exiſtence of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Proteſtantiſme he doth not once touch it, till the Albigenſes began 1170. years after Chriſt, wherein it is alſo moſt evident, that he gaineth little to his purpoſe, though after much ſtrugling. All this muſt needs convince what before in groſs was decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from conſent of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and the conſtant ſenſe of the whole Church.</p>
               <p>I anſwer thirdly: As Chriſtians have in all ages upon the ſame pretences
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:124528:16"/>replied to ſectaries, that ſome of theſe points were more explicitly declared in the councel of <hi>Trent</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe new hereticks; but they were generally preached, &amp; every where, even by the <hi>Greeks</hi> beleev'd before, as all writers even our adverſaries confeſs: Nay, <hi>Luther's</hi> own writings free the councel of <hi>Trent</hi> from this calumny, becauſe he accuſed the Church of all theſe things before the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> was dreamed of; it being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocated to repreſs his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations, or new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnations of theſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral received truths: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe not <hi>Luther,</hi> but thoſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:124528:16"/>Catholicks which firſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him, had been noted and accuſed of novelty by the reſt of the body of the Church: And further, no man is ignorant, that before the Councel of <hi>Trent, England</hi> by <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, by B. <hi>Fiſher,</hi> by Sir <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> in his works, as alſo in his Tindal, <hi>&amp;c. Germany</hi> by <hi>Eckins, Daven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius, Verveſius, Hofmeſterus,</hi> and others; yes the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church by infinite writers of that age, of this and the other part of the world, did riſe againſt theſe upſtarts, and laid novelty to their charge.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>England</hi> and other nations remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:124528:17"/>in their primitive and Apoſtolical faith, until the aforeſaid revolt; nay, theſe upſtarts themſelves never came to that impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, to accuſe Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks of novelties then ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but referred it to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; that is, latter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding ages, accuſing their forefathers of innovation; and this hath always been, and is the practiſe of up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarts: Therefore Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks who imbrace this faith derived from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by continual ſucceſſion, ought not to be too ſolicitous of the truth of it, ſeeing they hold it by conſtant ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:124528:17"/>and no way interupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>Neither will the breach which the Greeks have made from the Latins any way help them; becauſe they in <hi>England</hi> are as well broken from the Greeks, as they are from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans: which evidently appears, in that they can not give their letters of communication to them no more then to us. They hold the propitiatory ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Maſs; they hold Tranſubſtantiation, ſeven Sacraments, prayer for the dead, invocation of Saints, veneration of images, the Supremacy of <hi>a Tope,</hi> though ſome of them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:124528:18"/>exemption, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As <hi>Balſamon</hi> for the patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which <hi>Zonaras,</hi> though a Greek Schiſmatick acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be in the B. of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the reſt were accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do; nay <hi>Nilus,</hi> after he hath much violented authorities for his preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt the Popes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, in concluſion yeelds up the bucklers, and confeſſeth that they are bound to obey him in all lawful commands. I ſaid that the Greek Church ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth a Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: which I therefore ſaid, becauſe that ſome of thoſe who follow rigidly <hi>Photius</hi> his hereſie, touching
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:124528:18"/>the proceſſion of the holy Ghoſt, pretend that the Latin Church for that loſt the Supremacy, and <hi>ipſo jure et facto</hi> it was transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> but the Abettours of this laſt point are almoſt vaniſhed, as by divers councels, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the great <hi>Laterane, Linos,</hi> and laſt <hi>Florence</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councels ſufficiently appears, where it was not once arrogated, neither doth <hi>Hieremy</hi> their patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch, or any of their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior writers once ſay it. How ever this fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal rock of ſcandal of the ſea of <hi>Rom's</hi> Supremacy, if removed according to thoſe few <hi>Greeks</hi> pretences
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:124528:19"/>it would not avail you, for you deny any Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy: they grant this, and would onely chalenge it for themſelves injuriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which pretence is alſo ceaſed: Theſe are the ſtones of ſcandal betwixt you and us, which ye force all to abjure. So that the main Weſt and Eaſt Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches have nothing to do with you, ye are no mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of their communion; ſome ſmal conventicles you may finde here, and there in the Weſt in ſome things agreeing with you, though no notable part at all of your communion, no not in this very nation. But the Roman in her commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:124528:19"/>over all the world, communicates intirely without any diſſection of faith; we therefore have all ſecurity in religion: but the reaſon concerning Proteſtants is clean other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for ſeeing they have ſeparated themſelves from the Roman Church, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by the Apoſtles, the mother from whom they ſucked their faith; in which their forefathers lived, and continued, and what is proper to here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and ſchiſmaticks, they went out from us, (as <hi>St. Auguſtiue</hi> uſed the like argument againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts, fuſely and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently out of <hi>St. John</hi>)
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:124528:20"/>they I ſay, are bound to make inquiry into the cauſe of their ſeparation, and not ſo lightly beleeve the maſters of their error, and as it were one part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely heard to give ſenſe in a matter of ſo high concernment, but they ought diligently to hear the reaſons of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, and exactly to weigh all things on which their eternal ſalvation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, or if they fear any fallacies may be uſed by us in proof of our Religion, let them judiciouſly read the reaſons in <hi>Chollingworth</hi> which moved him to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Catholick, and counterpoiſe them with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:124528:20"/>thoſe which he puts down for his virtiginous revolt, and truly they will be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to confeſs, that the former are unanſwerable, and the latter wholy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable. The ground of our hopes of ſalvation dependeth upon the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of our faith, and therefore we muſt look into it, for as <hi>St. Auguſtine Cont. Lit. Petil.</hi> l. 1. c. 1. It is a dangerous thing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the haughty perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their forefathers with a more fooliſh obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy; neither doth it ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie as <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> there noteth <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5. if one ſhould ſay I will follow him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he made me a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:124528:21"/>for none preaching the name of Chriſt, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the Sacrament of Chriſt, is to be followed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the unity of Chriſt. This is often heard from the mouths of many of the wifeſt amongſt them; <hi>here I wax baptiſed, here I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main:</hi> but 'tis raw and filly to be born and baptiſed in this or the other Church, except it be in the unity of Chriſt; if from the other we or our forefathers have revolted, or been any way ſeperated, we muſt return from whence we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by ſchiſm or he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie. That therefore we may proceed in ſo weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a matter, with more
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:124528:21"/>care and ſolicitude, we will ſhew in the following Chapters in what danger of eternal damnation (I ſpeak not of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſon, whom how far invincible ignorance may excuſe, we leave to Gods ſecret counſel) they have miſerably precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and caſt themſelves headlong by ſeparating themſelves from the Church of Rome: I do not mean here to treate of the infinite ſubdiviſions of ſchiſm, which are this day riſen up within the lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Proteſtantiſm (as in time paſts amongſt the Donatiſts) and what ſort ſoever of ſeperatiſts have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:124528:22"/>always been, among whom they labour ſometimes to patch up together, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much as think to do it with Catholicks: but I will conſider how piouſly the Catholick root dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſeeketh the bough, that is broken from her, if the bough likewiſe ſhall labour to cloſe up that breach which is made by it. <hi>Auguſt. apud Baron.</hi> 411.</p>
               <p>Here therefore with all reaſon and truth may be averred, what Tertullian in his excellent book of praeſcriptions Chap. 29. religiouſly incultateth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſectaries: If your ſtate of diviſion is lawful; if your ſouls are
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:124528:22"/>ſecure in this lamentable ſeparation, the holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel hath been falſly taught to all the world, all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians have ſalſly beleeved; ſo many thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands falſly baptized; ſo many acts of faith; that is, all Sacraments falſly admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred; ſo many acts of religion; ſo many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles adulterouſly done; ſo many prieſthoods; ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sacrifices; laſt of all, ſo many Martyrdoms falſly undergone for the faith of Chriſt: all hath been in vain which in teſtimony of Chriſt hath been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, if Chriſt Church were not the Roman, in, and with her communion,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:124528:23"/>ſince there was no other acknowledged till ye came.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Catholicks may certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſaved.</head>
               <p>IT may be convinc'd with irrefragable arguments; that Catholicks in the Church of Rome remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, beleeving, and doing what ſhe propounds and preſcribes ſhall attain unto eternal ſalvation; which ſufficiently followeth out of what hath been ſaid in the firſt Chapter, if well
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:124528:23"/>attended; much more al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo might be produced from Chriſtian diſcourſing upon principles of holy Scripture and conſent of old and modern Doctors.</p>
               <p>But to bring our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors here is ſuperfluous labour, ſeeing Proteſtants with whom I have dealt ſincerely acknowledge, and ingeniouſly confeſs ſo much; and many of them of no ſmall account, have delivered in books that the Church of Rome is the Church of God, and that the errors in her, are not ſo much as do overthrow the foundation of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and therefore with them many have and may
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:124528:24"/>now be ſaved: So <hi>Morton, Regn. Jer. page</hi> 94. the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are to be thought of the Church of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they hold the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Goſpel, which is faith in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the Son of God. <hi>Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Eccleſ. Polit. page</hi> 140. we willingly acknowledge Papiſts to be of the family of Chriſt. <hi>Covel. Apol. ad Archep. Cant.</hi> we affirm thoſe who are of the Churh of Rome to be part of the Church of Chriſt, and thoſe who live and die in the Church of Rome may notwithſtanding be ſaved: and he accuſeth the Puritans of ignorance that think the contrary.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:124528:24"/>
                  <hi>Soame, Apol. p.</hi> 146. if you think that all Papiſts that die in the Papiſtical Church are damned, you think abſurdly, and you diſſent from the judgment of learned Proteſtants. D. <hi>Burlo</hi> in his 3. <hi>Sermon ad Clerum</hi> ſaith: I dare not deny, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> D. <hi>Laud,</hi> late Arch-Biſhop of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in his great volume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Jeſuite, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not of ordinary Papiſts ſalvations; and of late Doctor <hi>Taylour</hi> in his liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Prophecying; out of his principles neceſſarily concludes ſo much in his twentieth Paragraph, and number the 3<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> he ſpeaks thus. They keep the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:124528:25"/>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore all the wiſeſt perſonages of the adverſe party allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them poſſibility of Salvation, whileſt their errors are not faults of their will, but weakneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and deceptions of the underſtanding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The foundation of faith ſtands <hi>ſecure enough</hi> for all theſe vain and unhandſome ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructures, <hi>&amp;c. Chilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> hath both the ſame tenents frequently, and as you may gather by his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of expreſſion, he grants them, yet very plainly, though unwillingly; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he ſaith that they are not damnable, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that they are damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:124528:25"/>in themſelves; but <hi>not to Catholicks</hi> except they ſtick to them out of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of error: It was well he added this, elſe he had in one ſtroke broken the whole phantaſtick fabrick of his verbal, not rational volume, flaſhy, no way ſubſtantial, as any ſober man will judge.</p>
               <p>The whole reſult of his work, is; that every man beleeving Scriptures, and feriouſly labouring to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a <hi>probable</hi> ſence out of them, is ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for in order to his ſalvation; which is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a neceſſity of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with any in point of Religion, as every man
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:124528:26"/>ſeeth againſt all Scripture, and the Creed. This is by the way.</p>
               <p>There are indeed ſome amongſt them, as <hi>Field, Uſher,</hi> and others, who ſeem ſomtimes to ſpeak more rigidly touching Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks Salvation.</p>
               <p>But they obſerve not how repugnant this is to a generally admitted, and cried up principle amongſt them; which is this, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they differ not from us in fuundamentals or neceſſaries.</p>
               <p>By this they labour hard to make their breach from from us, not to be damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, being they differ not in points of neceſſary be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:124528:26"/>
               <p>Which if it hath force, doth it not inevitably, and with more ſtrength con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a ſecurity for us?</p>
               <p>We muſt therefore conclude, that whether they will or no, they do all conclude a poſſibility of ſalvation for us, adhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our faith delivered from our forefathers; and to omit innumerable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, King <hi>James</hi> ſhall ſerve for all, for he ſpeaks in the name of all in his ſpeech to the Parliament, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 9. 1605. we right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (ſaith he) confeſs that many Papiſts, eſpecially our progenitors, putting their onely truſt in Jeſus Chriſt, and his merits,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:124528:27"/>may, and are frequently ſaved, deteſting according to that, and judging the cruelty of the Puritans worthy of fire, who will grant no ſalvation to any Papiſts. Yea, D. <hi>Potter</hi> in his book ſet forth by the command of King <hi>Charles, pag.</hi> 76. &amp; 77. confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that thoſe things which Proteſtants think erroneous in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, are not in themſelves damnable to thoſe who beleeve as they profeſs; and that all may be ſaved with them, who <hi>bona fide</hi> beleeve and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Roman Religion, as long as they finde no motives ſufficient where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:124528:27"/>their judgment is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, that they be in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. To conclude all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of any moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who are not poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the tincture of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid <hi>Calviniſme,</hi> freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that Catholicks in their religion may be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and do accuſe them of want of Charity, that they do not think ſo of them. So our adverſaries are our judges, as appears by their own confeſſion, that we may attain unto ſalvation in the Church of Rome. I could give you a longer liſt, but it were ſuperfluous in a confeſſed doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:124528:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Schiſm is an enormous Crime.</head>
               <p>SChiſm, if we look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the force of the word, it ſignifieth diviſion; if it be in the civil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, it is called Sedition; if in the Church, Schiſm; or the ſame word may be uſed for both, and be diſtinguiſhed by Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thites: in the one caſe it is civil Sedition, in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſtical Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Church may be divided two wayes; firſt, by revolting from faith,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:124528:28"/>which doth not only make Schiſm but hereſie: hence it is that they who fall from the faith and doctrin of the Church, ſetting up their contrary opinions, as Arrians, Macedonians, and the like, are not onely termed Sciſmaticks, but Hereticks. Secondly, the Church is divided by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting from the chief Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, or general Councels by diſobedience; or from communion with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther members, although faith be conſerved intire: and this makes pure Schiſm as it is diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from hereſie. So the Donatiſts, and Meletians at firſt keeping the faith of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:124528:29"/>the Church, but abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from communion with the other members in divine worſhip, prayer, and other holy rites; or when they erected altar againſt altar, then, and not before, they were properly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Schiſmaticks; from whence it is gathered that although Schiſm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing, is wont to degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into hereſie, becauſe as <hi>St. Hierom</hi> ſaith in <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. There is no Schim which doth not frame to it ſelf ſome hereſie, that they may ſeem to have juſt cauſe to revolt from the Church: Hence <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> l. 2. <hi>contra Creſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium</hi> c. 7. Schiſm is a new
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:124528:29"/>revolt; Hereſie is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate Schiſm: yet ſpeaking in rigour hereſie violating the faith of the Church, Schiſm breaking her charity, they are both grevious ſins, ſeeing they ſeperate from the Church, and conſequently from the head, which is Chriſt. But now we will onely treat of the greviouſneſs of Schiſm.</p>
               <p>There are a ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who cannot conceive, that a Chriſtian Common-wealth, remaining obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the civil Magiſtrate, can be guilty of Schiſm: becauſe they do ſo far ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Eccleſiaſtical perſons and cauſes to civil magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:124528:30"/>that they do ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical <hi>power</hi> at all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiſtinct from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral in a Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; except in things internal: as Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> holds, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. <hi>n.</hi> 21, 22. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though afterwards he gives ſome ſmal no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things to them: he will have the Prince ſupreme, even in ſpirituals; <hi>c.</hi> 18. <hi>n.</hi> 13. and therefore they muſt depend on the Prince in the uſe of all; and at laſt in his laſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and number, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales all he had granted. The truth is, he is ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in his ſtructure of a civil Common-wealth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:124528:30"/>(wherein he hath ſome excellent things) that he either neglects, or redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the ſpiritual common-weath or Church almoſt to a Platonical inexiſtent Idea.</p>
               <p>Reaſon tells us, that as natural, ſo moral powers and offices are known to be ſpecifically different, and not onely numerically diſtinct by their ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations; the difference of operations is known by their ſeveral objects, or ſometime by the very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral tending to the ſame ſpecifical object as Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers know.</p>
               <p>Now the offices of eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical and civil magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:124528:31"/>are obviouſly known to have theſe ways to declare their real and ſpecifical differences. <hi>St. Paul</hi> in his fifth chapt. to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> even from the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſufficiently declares it from their operations and objects, and tells us that the Prieſt is taken to his office from <hi>amongſt men:</hi> by men is underſtood the temperal power, from whence this other power is ſevered by <hi>St. Paul.</hi> I wiſh the ingenuous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to peruſe it all, and compare Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> his grounds to <hi>St. Paul</hi> and what I annex in the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>I am ſure beſides ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:124528:31"/>the judgement o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ancient Chriſtians was fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> otherwiſe. There were bounds for eccleſiaſtical and temporal magiſtracy alwayes acknowledged great <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>to theſe who obſerve Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary life</hi> to this purpoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeth, and applaudeth an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> epiſtle of <hi>Hoſius</hi> of <hi>Cordub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Arriar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Emperor. <hi>Ceaſe I beſeech thee and remember that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> art mortal, fear the day of judgment, intermeddle not with eccleſiaſtical matters, neither do thou command us in this kinde, but rather learn them of us; to thee God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Empire, to us he hath committed the things that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:124528:32"/>belong to the Church: and as he who with malicious eyes carpeth thine Empire, gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayeth the ordinance of God: ſo do thou alſo beware, leaſt in drawing to thee Eccleſiaſtical matters, thou be made guilty of a horrible crime: It is written, give ye the things that are</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars <hi>to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>and the things that are Gods to God: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither is it lawful for us in earth to hold the Empire, neither haſt thou (O Emperor) power over incenſe and ſacred things.</hi> This extent is far beyond internals, or Mr. <hi>Hobb's</hi> limits. <hi>St. Ambroſe</hi> alſo to <hi>Valentinian</hi> in his fifth book of Epiſtles in his oration of delivering up of Churches (<hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:124528:32"/>by ill adviſe of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Juſtina</hi> an Arrian, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to have one Church deputed in Milan for the Arrians) ſaith thus, <hi>We pay that which is</hi> Caeſars <hi>to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>and that which is Gods to God: Tribute is</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars, <hi>it is not denied: The Church is Gods, it may not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be yeelded to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Temple of God cannot be</hi> Caeſars <hi>right. Which no man can deny but it is ſpoken with the honour of the Empire; for what is more honorable then that the Emperor be ſaid to be the Son of the Church, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> good Emperor is within the Church, not above the Church</hi> He is diametpically oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to Mr. <hi>Hobbs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:124528:33"/>
               <p>Out of theſe, and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite other texts, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of antiquity it is moſt clear; that all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians grounded upon Scriptures, as they concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, did beleeve that the Church taken rigidly, and ſtrictly was underſtood to conſiſt onely of ſpiritual men; and a city, or a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth did, and doth import a body of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans conſidered as not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to divine ſervice and functions, but as members of the civil or temporal body: and that therefore though as civil perſons, they were ſubject onely to this, or that city or country, namely in civil
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:124528:33"/>or temporal things, yet in Eccleſiaſtical they might be ſubject to Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical power; though ſometimes ſeated in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain countries, (Spiritual things are not circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by place) and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently my own temporal Prince according to <hi>St. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> might be a fellow ſubject with me in this; which depends not at all upon the temporal power, but is wholy of another, and a higher nature; though Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> denies it, which I wonder at; reaſon me-thinks will neceſſarily carry us to prefer ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al before temporal: and therefore <hi>St. Peter</hi> in his
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:124528:34"/>firſt Epiſtle Chap. 2. calls temporal magiſtracy a <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man creature,</hi> that is in a peculiar way derived from man: But <hi>St. Paul Acts</hi> 20. ſpeaking of Eccleſiaſtical magiſtracy ſaith, the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> hath placed you <hi>to rule</hi> the Church of God: and <hi>St. Ignatius</hi> contempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary to the Apoſtles, gives us his own, and the ſenſe of Chriſtians in thoſe days, when he exhorts the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Smyrna in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to them, firſt to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God, next the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and then the King.</p>
               <p>They are not therefore in the ſenſe of Chriſtians the ſame thing, a Biſhop, and Chriſtian King, nor
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:124528:34"/>their office the ſame; the one tending immediately to things which belong to God in order to ſouls: The other immediatly to things of this world, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to the external peace of Subjects; though ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily with reference to God alſo, but the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical by ſupernatural me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums; the other proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by natural, which is more remote and indirect; and therefore <hi>St. Paul</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> cap. 5. ſaith, this power is converſant <hi>circa ea quae ad Deum ſunt,</hi> which is no where <hi>ſimply</hi> aſſerted of the other, and in the law thoſe are called <hi>Sors Domini</hi> in a peculiar ſtrain.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:124528:35"/>
               <p>And to ſpeak truth Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> had done very well, if he had taken <hi>St. Paul</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with him in framing his new model of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian City; who diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth each members office very often.</p>
               <p>All authority is not in the Princes, but <hi>Hebrews</hi> 13. lay people are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to obey their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſts, and to be ſubject to them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where he ſufficiently diſtinguiſheth the Tribunals. No Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can be ignorant of the authority which the Holy Ghoſt giveth to Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates <hi>regere Eccleſiam Dei</hi> to govern the Church of God; ſo that this ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:124528:35"/>government is of God; and it is a <hi>government,</hi> and therefore not onely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative or inſtructive, as Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> ſaith even of Chriſt himſelf, <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>n.</hi> 13. but it is a regitive power, els <hi>S. Peter</hi> had moſt heavily tranſgreſſed his commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in adjudging <hi>Ananias,</hi> and after his wife <hi>Saphira</hi> to preſent death for a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual crime: <hi>St. Paul</hi> in his excommunicating the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator: <hi>St. John</hi> and the reſt had abuſed their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er alſo; which I touch in the ſeventh Chapter, who went beyond pure decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their guilt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected not the cities ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in it. Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:124528:36"/>indeed in Paſtours a power to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute a ſpiritual ſentence, in caſe the Church, that is the city judgeth of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Prieſts may abſolve, if the city judgeth it fit, elſe not. <hi>St. Athan.</hi> in the place cited. <hi>Quando ab avo condito auditum eſt;</hi> Mark M. <hi>Hobbs, Quando judicium Eccleſiae authoritatem ſuam ab Imperatore accepit</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was never heard from the beginning of the world, that the Church hath her power from tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral power. In earneſt I wiſh he had taken the ſence of Chriſtians along with him; in his expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:124528:36"/>holy Scriptures, he ſhould have read the old Councels in making Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical lawes, which power Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors ſubmitted unto as from God: <hi>Conſtantine</hi> in the <hi>Nicen, Martian, Leo,</hi> and all others whom the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world eſteemed not Antichriſtian, as they did <hi>Conſtantius</hi> for intrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>St. Nazianzen</hi> in his ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in diſputations, tells us that Praelates have power to <hi>make lawes,</hi> &amp;c. in order to the ſoul. <hi>St. Damaſcen</hi> in his ſecond oration of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages ſaith, <hi>Kings have no power to preſcribe lawes unto
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:124528:37"/>the Church,</hi> and proves it out of <hi>St. Paul</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhews, that in framing the Church of God; that is, in declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſts model of his Church, St. <hi>Paul</hi> never at all mentioneth Kings.</p>
               <p>In fine: I finde all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity from the infancy to theſe daies growth to have conveyed to us this ſence, as delivered from Chriſt without contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>Which Topicks, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon, by reaſon Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> will not be thought to reject them, neither doth he uſe any other conſiderable principles, though ſometimes he glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:124528:37"/>at heavie inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences to a civil common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, if this be granted. But I am not willing to take too much notice of it, leaſt any might fear his aim to be, to deſtroy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion: for ſurely the Romans inſiſted moſt upon that, as the Roman Hiſtories ſhew, and it is clear in <hi>Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
               <p>All which the very great Turk admits as a truth; namely, a ſpiritual power of governing among Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, moſt conſiſtent with his ſupreme rights over Chriſtians; and therefore ſtumbleth not at the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual power of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:124528:38"/>of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which he exerciſeth over Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and correſponds with them in this kinde, though not ſubject to the Turk; and therefore Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> needs not fear in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, what the Turk doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not. Out of all this it followeth, that there may be Schiſm in defect of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, in order to the Church, without breach of duty to the Prince.</p>
               <p>Sacriledge of Schiſms ſaith St. <hi>Auguſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>cont. ep. Far. c.</hi> 4. exceedeth all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther crimes: and St. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom.</hi> gives the reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cut and divide the great and glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, and as much
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:124528:38"/>as in them lieth kill it: and therefore as he who ſhould tear in <hi>peices</hi> the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or members of a man, ſhould be thought to do the greateſt injury and damage: So he who divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Church, which is the body of Chriſt, which he ſo loved, that he gave himſelf for it, doth commit a grievious fin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
               <p>Therefore we finde in holy ſcripture no crime more grievouſly puniſhed, or revenged with a more dreadful torment, then Schiſm.</p>
               <p>For when <hi>Core, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiron</hi> (by whom what other things is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:124528:39"/>ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> l. <hi>de</hi> 42. <hi>manſi. manſ.</hi> 15. then, thoſe who bring Schiſm Hereſie into the Church) had ſeparated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by wicked Schiſm from <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> not onely they but their wives and children with all their ſubſtance were ſwallowed up into the earth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended alive into hell: <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. &amp; this truly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to them viſibly, to be an argument to future ages, how enormous the crime of Schiſm is before God, &amp; to deter men from plotting or following the ſame.</p>
               <p>Neither are preſent Schiſmaticks puniſh'd with
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:124528:39"/>leſſer paines, though they appear not to our eyes. By the aforeſaid example St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ep. 164. writing to <hi>Emiritus</hi> the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, gathereth how much this crime of Schiſm is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed in the divine judgment. Read, which I make no doubt you have read, you ſhall finde <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and <hi>Abiron</hi> devoured by opening of the earth, the reſt who conſented to them conſumed with fire, being in the midſt of them. Therefore our Lord God brandeth that ſin with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent puniſhment, as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to be avoided; that whom he patiently ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſuch he ſheweth to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:124528:40"/>reſerve to the laſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For as the ſame St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> elſewhere ſaith: whoſoever is ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Gatholick Church, although he thinketh he liveth lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; for this onely fin, that he is disjoynted from the unity of Chriſt he ſhall not have life, but the anger of God remains upon him and after him: St. <hi>Fulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius de fide ad Pet.</hi> c. 39. Hold certainly &amp; doubt not, that what Schiſmatick or Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſoever, is baptiſed in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, if he be not joyned to the Catholick Church, what alms ſoever he ſhall do,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:124528:40"/>though alſo he ſhall ſpill his blood for Chriſt, can never be ſaved. In fine; we need not go further then to bleſſed St. <hi>Paul</hi> to learn the horror of Schiſm, who in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. If I ſhould ſpeak with the tongues of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and not have Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I am but as braſs ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or a Cymbal gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling; and if I have the gift of propheſie, and ſhall know all miſteries and all ſciences; and if I have ſo great faith, as to remove mountains; yet if I have not Charity I am nothing: If I ſhall diſtribute all I have amongſt the poor; if I deliver my body up to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:124528:41"/>the fire; if I have not Charity, that is; if I ſhall adhere to Schiſm, all is worth nothing. A heavy ſentence, if deeply conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: Alas, what will follow out of this, St. <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrin touching all thoſe whom we have known, and of others whom yet we do know; who have been of untouched lives, liberal to the poor, of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inclinations, or what you will; all is loſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> being they were members of this Sciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical body.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, who do not onely in themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void Schiſm, and keep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violated the Church uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:124528:41"/>but where they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any danger of breach, each man in his rank and degree indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with all his poſſible diligence to preſerve it; they piouſly and laudably beſtow themſelves and their endeavours, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly merit much of God and man. Of ſuch it may be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, that the Charity of their neighbour doth urge them, and the love of God as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>de Trinit.</hi> doth divide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the children of the eternal kingdom, and the children of eternal perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thinking, and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they have not the charity of God, who do not
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:124528:42"/>love his Church, &amp; as much as in them do not procure her unity: It is all one from what head inſolent diſobedience ſpringeth, from whence floweth Schiſm; or I would ſay the reaſon of Schiſm is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in it ſelf, for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe motive of rebellion; for whether from the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of Biſhops, as too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it happneth, of which we have ſad examples in Hiſtories; or whether from emulation of equals: or to conclude, for what cauſe ſoever of the pride of ſubjects it ariſeth; if it maketh ſeparation it is Schiſm, and divorceth the ſouls of all thoſe that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:124528:42"/>&amp; knowingly adhere unto it, as from the union of the Church, ſo from the love of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I am not ignorant what the ſchool men teach in a ſpeculative ſenſe touching the extent and effects of invincible ignorance, in order not onely to Schiſm but Hereſie; but we ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract now from ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or from caſes which are accidental or onely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginary: and therefore conſidering Schiſm as it is underſtood in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and practical notion, which the word gives in the ſence of Chriſtians; I have univerſally conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that it ſeparateth us
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:124528:43"/>from the love of Chriſt, and conſequently from heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Catholicks and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants divided by Schiſm.</head>
               <p>VVE ſaid before, that Schiſm was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time taken for Separation from the Catholick faith, ſometimes taken for ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from communion onely, although faith be kept entire. Now what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may be ſaid of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:124528:43"/>Schiſm of the firſt kind, of which for the preſent I do not treat: we ſay that Proteſtants are divided and ſeparated from Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, whom they terme Papiſts, at leaſt by Schiſm of the latter kinde, and that appears ſo manifeſtly; that it needeth no proof; for not onely Catholicks and Proteſtants do ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor mutual communion in divine worſhip, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, prayer, and holy rites; that no Proteſtant will frequent Catholick ſervice, eſpecially the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſacrifice of Maſs: and every Catholick will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void whatſoever is eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed religious among Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:124528:44"/>as the bread of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and eſteem all that ſhall but touch them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taminate and defiled.</p>
               <p>Moreover, Catholicks excommunicate Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants every year, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants Catholicks fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in <hi>England,</hi> yea they exhauſt ſuch as in law ſhall be convicted with pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniary mulcts; and by the publick ſtatutes and lawes of the Land, any one who ſhall convert a a Proteſtant to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick faith, is guilty of death, but a Prieſt who ſhall celebrate Maſs is made guilty of high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. How therefore can one Church grow up toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:124528:44"/>of ſuch different members? Or who will deny that here is manifeſt Schiſm and diviſion, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any Schiſm was or can be made?</p>
               <p>O how far is this from the ſpirit of old Chriſtians: they gloried in that which the ancient called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a ſweet, humane, or neighbourly tenderneſs to delinquents of this kinde. Spiritual ſins the old Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church cured by ſpiritual Cataplaſms, at moſt proportioned to them; when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained not themſelves within the compaſs of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituallity, but made e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions into ſedition, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:124528:45"/>diſturbance of the publick peace; then their Authors juſtly loſt the benefit of Eccleſiaſtical mildneſs, and taſted ſometimes the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial ſeverity, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out death for many ages: If our perſecutors would limit their cruelties within this verge, it would be leſs execrable; they complain of the ſeverity of Q. <hi>Maries</hi> daies, and yet far exceed what they condemn in her.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hobb's</hi> will put a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in theſe caſes, for <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. <hi>n.</hi> 5. he tels us that Princes do againſt conſcience, who permit their ſubjects to practice a religion, which they judge
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:124528:45"/>to be damnable to them. This was Q. <hi>Maries</hi> caſe as all know; but the caſe is far otherwiſe with us, for it is evident that our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have profeſſed, with their Doctors, that Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be had in our Church; and therefore according to Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> they ſhould not diſquiet their ſubjects in uſing their liberty in their Religion. But to let Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> paſs, and come a little neerer to the buſineſs, I will ſay one thing (though not tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon me to diſcuſs or excuſe her proceedings in every particular) that the ſtate of the queſtion is wholy changed: She pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:124528:46"/>for <hi>innovation</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Jewes, Turks, and the very Romans was reckoned a moſt enormous crime. Theſe puniſh us becauſe we will not <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate,</hi> but ſtick cloſe to the religion of our and their forefathers; a crime un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of amongſt all who have had any taſte of God, but moſt eſpecially among true Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Many indeed have for ſome years cryed out for immunitie, in order to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſciences: and yet they themſelves; who were the heads of thoſe Tenderlings, did not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to have Recuſants
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:124528:46"/>accounted ſuch, who have title to it above all, all things conſidered, as being beſt able to manifeſt to the world, their reluctancie in matter of conformity to all <hi>Changeable</hi> religions. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to be grounded upon true tenderneſs of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that is upon religious fear of offence of God, and yet for this they are moſt ſtrictly treated.</p>
               <p>Is it not an unparalel'd exorbitancy with ſuch high cruelties, as quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, hanging, and ſetting up the diſſerted quarters upon gates, and cittadels for fouls to tear, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, of perſons moſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in their lives towards
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:124528:47"/>God, and mens lawes, moſt quiet in order to the weal publick; onely for imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, or teaching that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Chriſt, which our and their forefathers in this nation followed for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a thouſand years: a crime moſt horridly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the firſt principles of nature. Is it not parri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide thus to profane the urnes of their forefathers? Is it not to the uttermoſt of their power, to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the forenamed cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon them their own progenitors; in doing them upon thoſe who are guilty of no other crime, then what they knowingly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and endeavoured to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:124528:47"/>transfuſe to their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Their ſanguinary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt theſe, clearly maketh known to the world their hearts ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous and bloudy ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor even againſt their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</p>
               <p>They commonly ſay, that they do not puniſh us for religion, but for acts of treaſon or fellony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but it is not ſo common as impertinent: Thus all perſecutors of Chriſtians did palliate their cruelties. The Roman Hiſtoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers will tell us, it was for ſedition that thoſe cruel perſecutions were againſt us, the Jewes thus labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to baptiſe their falſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:124528:48"/>accuſations againſt our bleſſed Saviour, and after againſt St. <hi>Paul, Minutius, Felix,</hi> and other antient writers, as <hi>Euſebius, Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> &amp;c. will tell you of Chriſtians accuſed of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate conventicles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all their lawes when they had their religious ſolemnities. Thus <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> to take the glory of Martyrdom from our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant religious progenitors laboured to deceive the vulgar. The Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors made many edicts, and ſome capital againſt all Chriſtian conventions: <hi>Julian</hi> againſt Chriſtians children frequenting their Schooles; againſt Biſhops
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:124528:48"/>reſiding in their Seas, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For this point of debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Chiſtians from their ſchools, he had a ſpecious prenence, which he ſhrewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly urged, that is, becauſe the Authors who taught in Schools (Chriſtians being not yet ſo commonly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Sciences) were Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks, and therefore we had no title to them; but this is far otherwiſe with you, for all your learning is ours: examine all your Schools fee the prefection of your ſtudies of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, Theolgie, Can on or civil law, Phiſick, are they not all ours? Nay, are not the founders of all Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges ours? And yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:124528:49"/>
                  <hi>Julian</hi> ye debar us of our own Schools. The truth is the laws are made againſt religion, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the propagation of it, againſt the profeſſing of it, in frequenting Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, onely admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by Prieſts.</p>
               <p>When a town or caſtle is beſieged, convoys ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, all hanged who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to bring ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, viures, hath any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with them; are not theſe in this caſe perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for their allegiance, if they expoſe themſelves to all theſe dangers out of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to their Prince, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is Supreme Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty? This is our caſe, ye
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:124528:49"/>hang and quarter all who would bring unto us ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ammunition, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental vivers, by death ye obſtruct all convoys, and why all this? Is it not to extirpate our religion; is it not to force us to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſmall holds we have, wherewith God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath intruſted us, of his holy religion in our Souls?</p>
               <p>There are ſome who would ſeem to aboliſh all perſecution from Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, in blood and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, pretending it to be injuſtice to perſecute for religion; and upon this glorious title of Chriſtian liberty, and neighbourly
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:124528:50"/>tenderneſs, do cover ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice beyond all proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſtians, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Jews, or of the Turks, even againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſubject to their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil empire; and truly what human nature ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors, namely to take their children from them, and educate them in their own aiery and uncertain wayes. The Church of God in her moſt flouriſhing times as under <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoſius,</hi> when all Inſidels and Jewes were under their power, never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted ſuch a cruelty, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of nature.</p>
               <p>Nay, the Turks never do it, except upon faile of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:124528:50"/>their ordinary exactions: which truly are nothing to the burthens of Catholicks here. If it be unlawful to perſecute (as they hold) in their fortunes for religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, its moſt in conſequent to hold it more lawful to perſecute in children. Lands and goods are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated onely, <hi>jure gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> children <hi>jure naturae:</hi> wherein no power, except God himſelf can diſpenſe. To take away goods or land, is theft or rapine: This muſt be reduced to Homicide. Nature is ſo little acquainted with it, that there is not a proper appellative yet appointed for it. Chriſtian Divines out of this principle have
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:124528:51"/>judged it unlawful even to baptiſe Infidels, or Jewes children againſt their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents wills, by reaſon of the high title of the natural law of parents to children: hence ſome have taught, that baptiſm ſo attempted would not be valid. But to let that paſs; here is a <hi>forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ori,</hi> as Logitians ſpeak, concluded: That to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs parents of their children, in all ſchools of Chriſt, of law, of reaſon, is abominable; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I cannot beleeve, that our laws will admit ſuch acts to be lawful: eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſince by precedent Sanctions its already felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to take away children
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:124528:51"/>upon any pretences.</p>
               <p>There are yet another ſort, who ſeem more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then all the reſt; and pretend to reduce all to an <hi>Henoticon,</hi> or <hi>Unitive;</hi> namely, that we may all in offenſively retain our own faith, referring the examine of all differences to Gods court, to whom alone as the gift of faith; ſo the animadverſion or puniſhment of tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in it proportionably and conſequently is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, as they ſay: what real effect will this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce time will diſcover, if they proceed conſequently to their principles, it muſt needs take away many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian-like
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:124528:52"/>animoſities, which hitherto have been nouriſhed. <hi>Michael Balbut,</hi> as <hi>Zonaras</hi> in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals witneſſeth, promiſed in the beginning of his Empire, that he would not compel any to follow any other opinions of God, then what each man would himſelf: but ſoon after he perſecuted Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks cruelly, permitting all others to do what they liſted, he was a man indeed full of all wickedneſs. But <hi>Joſephus l.</hi> 2. againſt <hi>Apion</hi> ſaith, that it was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable in the Romans, that they would not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel their ſubjects to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late their <hi>ancient</hi> lawes and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:124528:52"/>neligion; but content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſuch honors and duties, as the giver may with piety and equity give them: for they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count not of forced ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, or duties, which come of compulſion. A courſe certainly worth all Princes obſerving in order to their ſubjects, and the onely way to be ſecure of their loyalties; as the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of <hi>France</hi> in order to Proteſtants, and <hi>Holland</hi> to Catholicks manifeſtly ſhew. However, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent out of theſe premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that there is a great Schiſm betwixt us in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Proteſtants are wont
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:124528:53"/>to ſay, that they are not ſeparated from Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, or the Catholick Church, no not from the Roman; but that they do communicate with all the members thereof, fearing and worſhiping God truly, and make one Church with them: they onely ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate themſelves from Papiſtry; which is not (ſay they) the Church, but an Impoſture, adhering to the Church, or an heap of errors brought into the Church, by the tyranny and fraud of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome.</hi> That they and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks are not two fields, ſepatated the one from the other, but one; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:124528:53"/>one part is covered with nettles and darnel, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſowed by the Pope, but the other part is purged by the labour and induſtry of the Proteſtants; but this if it were true, doth not infringe, but rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm what we have ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: for when we ſee with our eyes Catholicks and Proteſtants to abhor from mutual communion, who in his wits will deny that there is Schiſm and diviſion betwixt them; or who will affirm, there is any unity among them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to make one Church? And that they add, that they are ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Papiſtry, and the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:124528:54"/>errors of the Pope; that they are as it were the one part of the field, purged and cleanſed; Catholicks the other part covered with errors: Although all this were granted (which yet is never to be granted) it makes nothing at all to the diminiſhing, but adds much to the augmenting of Schiſm, becauſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this, Proteſtants are not onely ſeparated from the communion of Catholicks, which is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for Schiſm; but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from the doctrin, which as I ſaid before ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hereſie. So whileſt they ſtrive to take away, or patch up Schiſmatical
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:124528:54"/>diviſion, they bring in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical confuſion; which is much more pernitious, and more difficultly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Catholicks.</p>
               <p>Therefore it remains for certain, that there is a true Schiſm betwixt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks and Proteſtants, the queſtion will be onely to ſee, which of theſe made firſt the breach.</p>
               <p>The other main <hi>Achilles</hi> which they uſe, that they withdraw themſelves from the obedience of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> without Schiſm; is, becauſe he had onely Patriarchall power over them, introduced onely by human right, and cuſtom, is frivolous for to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:124528:55"/>omit that right, that he hath from Chriſt over the whole Church which is Papal.</p>
               <p>I will onely give this touch.</p>
               <p>We indeed are principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accuſed for adhering to the Popes ſupremacy as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a novelty: But how clearly it was acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the 4 firſt councels, needs no other proofs then themſelves: Nay, <hi>Tertullian, St. Cyprian, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus,</hi> the firſt writers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it, though in ſome perticulars they were offended with the Popes. <hi>Tertullian</hi> though perſecuted for Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, by that ſea; yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:124528:55"/>the power. 1. de pudicitia: <hi>Audio edictum eſſe propoſitum et quidem pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorium, Pontifer ſcilicet maximus,</hi> &amp;c. I underſtand that the Pope hath made a peremptory decree, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where he is angry at it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe againſt his hereſie, but doubteth not of his power. <hi>St. Cyprian,</hi> as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus</hi> in his notes confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, everywhere acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth it, even <hi>St. Stephen,</hi> and <hi>Cornelius</hi> his adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. <hi>Uſher</hi> who boggles at all things, becauſe <hi>St. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> calls <hi>Cornclius</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, would ſeem to doubt, but <hi>Eraſmus</hi> leſs ſquint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted will teach him, that it is in reſpect of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:124528:56"/>in faith, not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality of perſon. <hi>St. Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> is ſo vulgarly known, that all confeſs it. Nay, even <hi>Uſher,</hi> who ſeems to have ſworn to corrupt the cleareſt paſſages of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; yet confeſſeth in the buſineſs of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> that <hi>St. Victor</hi> Pope, did then pretend his ſupremacy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the reſt of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as appears in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tologue, as he calls it in the ſecond Century. So that it is no new title of the Popes, even according to <hi>Uſher;</hi> The full ſway of this great Bugbear in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry age, according to the enlargment of Chriſtian bounds, appears ſtill more
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:124528:56"/>gloriouſly in the Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the Church before, in, &amp; after the four Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels to <hi>St. Gregory:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I touch this no more. every Abodary contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſt forceth them to confeſs it to be truth.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> indeed <hi>c.</hi> 17. in the end of <hi>n.</hi> 26. denieth that there is, or can be a Rector of the univerſal Church, by whoſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity the whole Church may be convocated: He ventures alſo to prove it thus; becauſe to be a rector in that ſenſe, over the Church, is to be rector, and lord of all Chriſtians in the whole world, which is not granted to any but God.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:124528:57"/>
               <p>If he had been a ſtranger in Chriſtian principles, it had been no wonder to have miſunderſtood ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and publick a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. The Supreme Paſtor of the Church hath an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged power for preſervation of the Church in integrity of faith, to convocate Biſhops to a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral deliberation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation; and to this end he hath co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active power in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his ſpititual ſword, and no otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>What connexion this hath with a <hi>Dominion</hi> over the world, I know not, which by God himſelf is
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:124528:57"/>denied him in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and in this his power is diſtinguiſhed from tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral principality. His power is ſpiritual, his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons are ſpiritual, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to which he tends are ſpiritual: in this confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he commands with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice to temporal rights; wherein Princes are ſimply ſupreme, and onely have the coactive ſword of juſtice, indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently in reſpect of him, and this onely is domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>He thinks this too much, and therefore will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſubordination in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, out of each city
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:124528:58"/>or county; but every city is ſupreme to it ſelf in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Eccleſaſtical matters; and therefore no Prince, or city, or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church, can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated or interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing the antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the conſequence would without much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty be proved; for if the Prince is ſupreme in all things, he cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, which is an act of ſuperiority: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the common-wealth by it ſelf, for it were to diſſolve it ſelf into no ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if it ſhould deprive it ſelf of mutual commerce, which he acknowledgeth
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:124528:58"/>to be an effect of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication.</p>
               <p>But he leapes over the proof of the Antecedent, which had been indeed worth his doing by To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks fit for him, taken out of Scripture, antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or reaſon, ſubordinate to theſe principles. At leaſt, he ſhould have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an inconſiſtency of the publick welfare of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſubordination of particular Churches to a ſupreame, ſeated out of the temporal confines. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if there were not a moſt ordinate ſubordination, all religion would turn to a Hidraes confuſion, which
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:124528:59"/>were to deſtroy Chriſts acquired ſpiritual king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom on earth, and is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denlty againſt the light of reaſon, and one main arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Creed, which he accepteth of <hi>communion of Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The excellency of Chriſts kingdom is, that though univerſal; yet it troubleth not, but much conſerveth each kingdom in their particular Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy, though much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent betwixt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> in his city of God, <hi>Oroſtus</hi> in his Hiſtory; and many others againſt the Gentiles, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratively ſhew, the benefits all places receive,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:124528:59"/>by this ſpiritual ſubjection to Chriſtian principles: Amongſt which this was alwayes judged one of the moſt capital, as <hi>St. Deniſe, St. Ignatius,</hi> and the reſt ſhew of this Hierarchy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by God.</p>
               <p>He would tell us, not perſwade us, <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>n.</hi> 22. that all power, which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> exerciſed over particular Churches or Cities, was derived from the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of the Emperors, and was ſhaken off when their Empire was abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and in purſuit of this, he ſaith, that the Roman Church was indeed very large anciently, but always
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:124528:60"/>confined within the limits of the Empire.</p>
               <p>How falſe this is, no man can be ignorant, that hath peruſed antiquity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proſper,</hi> aſſures us, that <hi>Rome</hi> is made greater by the faith of Chriſt, then by the civil Empire, and ſo the reſt of the <hi>Fathers;</hi> but eſpecially he, <hi>de vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Gentium,</hi> l. 2. c. 16. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma per Apoſtolici Sacerdotij Principatum, amplior facta eſt arce religionis, quam ſolen Poteſtatis. St. Ireneus</hi> indeed tells us, that the reaſon why <hi>Rome</hi> was choſen for the head; was, becauſe it had been the head of the Empire, but none will ſay that it was confined by it,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:124528:60"/>or meaſured her ſpiritual territories by it. Who knows not that even in the Apoſtles time, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince vaſt Empires were reduced to this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Empire of <hi>Rome,</hi> which never had to do with the Romane Empire. Our own countries ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged ſubjection to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> under this title. <hi>Scotland</hi> alſo, and <hi>Ireland</hi> were moſt ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxly ſubject to the mitre, though not to the Scepter.</p>
               <p>This is onely by the by to Mr. <hi>Hobbs.</hi> But beſides this the Patriarchal right, which he hath over this our nation, cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:124528:61"/>by them: for by the ſame cauſes, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould be deſtroyed, by which it was ſet up; as the Juriſts agree: ſeeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath had his Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archal power granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him by general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels; to wit, by thoſe four firſt, which <hi>St. Gregory</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as four Goſpels, and eſpecially here by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limentary lawes, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed ſacred, it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth manifeſtly, that by leſs power then a general Councel it cannot be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed; for our Britany is one of the ſeven provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the weſtern Church, which are the ancient
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:124528:61"/>bounds of the Roman Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchate, as all know. In times paſt I grant, that the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> was called Patriarch by Pope <hi>Urbane</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, with <hi>Anſelme,</hi> and <hi>Malmes,</hi> and the <hi>Gloſſe. c. Clero. d.</hi> 21. as alſo the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Algar</hi> in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricts of <hi>Venice;</hi> but this was for honors ſake, not for exemption, as the thing it ſelf ſpeaketh, and the perpetual ſtile of the Church; yea, the very Councel of <hi>England</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince in <hi>Spelman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which were out of the Roman Empire, were ſubject to no Patriarch, as
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:124528:62"/>much as can be gathered out of the Canon of the Councel of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> except they put themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any one; or I think rather, that by law they ought to be ſubject to that Patriarch, from whom by his Apoſtolical Miſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, they firſt received the feith of Chriſt, <hi>ob ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem caſus Bulgarorum. Nam ſecundum Juriſtas; ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſimilis eſt ratio.</hi> As we argue of the <hi>Indies,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers lately converted <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponians,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>China.</hi> It is true, <hi>de facto,</hi> ſome Provinces againſt all Law, have revolted from the Patriarch of <hi>Rome,</hi> to the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:124528:62"/>after the diviſion of the Empire, and others from him to others: as <hi>Rusſia</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Moſcovia:</hi> but theſe are done againſt all lawes and government of the Church.</p>
               <p>The ſhift which our Country-men fly to, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they were compelled unto it, for the too much cruelty of the Pope, with the ſame facility it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected: for it ought to have been examined by a general Councel, and parts on both ſides be heard, as in the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> an excellent occaſion was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; (but ours appeared not) becauſe if it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for ſubjects to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:124528:63"/>themſelves from the obedience of their ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, as often as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend tyranny, or what op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion ſoever, ſo that themſelves be actors, and judges in their own cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, it is to be feared, that ſubjects of Princes, or whatſoever ſoeveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by this occaſion will lay hold on eaſie pretences of Rebellion: for if the reaſon be good, it is every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in force, and ſo any province out of apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of tyranny <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may juſtly, and lawfully with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw it ſelf from their Prince, or the Soveraign Magiſtracy.</p>
               <p>Therefore it remains
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:124528:63"/>firm: that ſeeing <hi>England</hi> by the moſt antient and ſtrong right was ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> neither hath that ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation been hitherto abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated by any lawful and ſufficient Councel; yea, neither the cauſe heard: therefore they ought to remain under obedience of the ſame ſea, until a full diſcuſſion of the matter; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſhe can be no wayes free from the crime of Schiſm and rebellion, according to that of <hi>St Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen,</hi> ep. 1. <hi>We deſire to know what this great luſt of bringing novations about the Church is, that every one that will:</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For if they who
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:124528:64"/>now make the ſtir had any thing that they might diſprove, or condemn in us, about faith: not ſo truly, we not being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, was it meet to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch a wickedneſs: For you ought to be willing either to perſwade, or be perſwaded (if ſo be alſo we are in any place or number, that who fear God and for the defence of the faith have undergone great labours, and have well deſerved of the Church) and then (if alſo then) we machinate new things, but notwithſtanding by this reaſon, theſe petulant and contumelious men might peradventure have ſome ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent excuſe.</hi> Behold how this great Saint, and Doctor of the Church maketh any
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:124528:64"/>receſs from the Church impoſſible and unlawful! The peſtilent poyſon of Schiſm, covered over with an ill plaiſter, may be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſound by impudent men: but truly except it be purged, and wiped to the very bottome of the ſoar with the plaiſter of Chriſtian peace, it will be Schiſm ſtill, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently bring death to thoſe that are infected with it.</p>
               <p>Some labour to cloak their Schiſm, and pretence of reformation under the fact of <hi>Ezechias. Reg.</hi> 4.18. The buſineſs is this: The Jewes had fallen into an inveterate cuſtome of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:124528:65"/>erecting altars, and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing incenſe upon the mountains to the brazen Serpent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> contrary to Gods command. The kings his predeceſſors were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reprehended for their neglect herein, and <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiah</hi> much commended for his zeal and fortitude in breaking this ill cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom.</p>
               <p>Hence they argue it lawful for kings to reform abuſes in the Church, as in <hi>England.</hi> All which is nothing to the purpoſe: For firſt, he did it with conſent of the high prieſt, as <hi>Joſias</hi> alſo did, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating the work begun by <hi>Ezekias,</hi> as appears <hi>c.</hi> 23.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:124528:65"/>Secondly, there is no doubt but Princes are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by their office, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nurſes of Gods Church, to labour eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with the Prelates of the Church, to ſuppreſs all emergent, inſolencies or innovations.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Which is the main point <hi>Ezechias</hi> did not erect any new al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of diviſion againſt the mother Church, <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> but took away the breach or diviſion which be found made by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>In the caſe of, <hi>England,</hi> it is juſt contrary. King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth began, the reſt have increaſed the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:124528:66"/>Schiſm, and erected new altars of diviſion, againſt Gods ordinances in the old and new law, as <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> did, <hi>Reg.</hi> 11.29. which God ſo ſeverely puniſhed. So that I cannot ſee at all, with what modeſtie this fact of <hi>Ezechias,</hi> or <hi>Joſias</hi> could be alledged to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the diſſection of our Country from the Church, ſince it plainly inferreth the contrary; namely, that abuſes, though never ſo much authorized by wicked Princes, or long cuſtoms are to be aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſucceeding Princes, to redintegrate the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry union, and conformity with the mother Church,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:124528:66"/>which is the caſe of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A main Objection which they uſe for their Schiſm is, becauſe as they ſay, we forbid a diſcuſſion of our tenents by the light of reaſon, which they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem to be againſt reaſon, which ſhould be our guide in all things, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in matters of religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:124528:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Of what uſe Reaſon is in diſouſſing of Faith.</head>
               <p>PHiloſophy and Faith go upon contrary princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and hence peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they lay hold of occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of error: the antiquity of opinion in Philoſophy, if it be any thing, it muſt be fortified with new reaſons, otherwiſe in proceſs of time it vaniſheth: but in Chriſtian faith, reaſon it ſelf, that it may be effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſpringeth from anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; otherwiſe, in that
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:124528:67"/>it is new, it vaniſheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, according to that of <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> againſt two E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles of the <hi>Pelagiuns</hi> c. 6. The antiquity of our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine declares the truth of it, as the novelty of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhews it to be Hereſie. In Philoſophy reaſon raigneth; here it ſerveth and conſequently is capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated according to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: It is not quite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, neither is it admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the bounds of a ſervant: for as <hi>Roger Bacon</hi> excellently ſpeaketh in his fourth part of his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter work: <hi>We do not ſeek reaſon before faith, but after it.</hi> Here was <hi>Chilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi>'s error, in objecting
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:124528:68"/>that Catholicks, as well as they, recur to reaſon in faith: we do indeed uſe reaſon as a ſervant, not as a miſtris. We put it, as Frier <hi>Bacon</hi> notes, after faith, not before it: but theſe new pretenders to divinity, prefer their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon before faith: Turn the cat in the pan, and make faith ſubſervient to their reaſon: as <hi>Teriullian</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Hermogenes.</hi> They deſcend from the Church to the School of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> they appeal as to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premeſt court, to the ſeat of common ſenſe, and as <hi>St. Baſil</hi> upon the 115. <hi>Pſal.</hi> They conſtitute their ſenſe the meaſure of all
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:124528:68"/>things; is not this to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the whole frame of Gods ſpiritual world? Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of <hi>St. Baſil</hi> in his 43. <hi>ep.</hi> As in things which are ſeen with the eyes, experience is of more conſideration then reaſon, ſo in the moſt excellent tenents of our faith is of more force, then any jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of reaſon. O how <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> meets with theſe ſocinians towards the end of his 56 Epiſtle! To theſe ſtraights they are driven, who finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt miſerably laid on their backs, when their authority is put in bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, to ſee how it will endure the teſt againſt
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:124528:69"/>the authority of the Church. They do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore endeavour, under the ſhew and promiſe of <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to quel the inmoveable authority of the holy Church; neither is it any news, for it is the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary practiſe of all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ticks: and in his, 22. <hi>Ep.</hi> he ſaith: That if a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick deſires a reaſon of his ſaith, that he may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what he beleeves, there muſt be an eye had to his capacity, that he may by reaſon obtain a proportionable meaſure of underſtanding; whence we learn, that's the regular diſcipline of hereticks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a falſe vizard of reaſon
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:124528:69"/>to lay aſide the moſt firm authority of Gods Church. Hence we alſo learn, how Catholicks make due uſe of reaſon, in matters of Faith, explicating holy myſteries according to each capacity.</p>
               <p>I wondered to finde Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> in his 12. <hi>Chap. n. 6.</hi> to be ſo poſitive, in attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting it to an error of the vulgar, to hold that Faith is not begotten by ſtudy, and natural reaſon. His principal ground is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it were impertinent to oblige us to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our Faith; that is, to render a reaſon of it as he would have it Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, if our reaſon doth
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:124528:70"/>not acquire it. Of how great force this his reaſon is, I leave any man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</p>
               <p>He deals fiercely againſt inſpiration of Faith; and ſaith, all the world is <hi>mad</hi> in aſſerting it, he conceives that every Chriſtian would be a prophet, if he had his Faith by ſupernatural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
               <p>Therefore in order to him, <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> and the reſt; and any who ſhall deſire to know in what manner, or how far Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks uſe the aſſiſtance of reaſon, perticularly in Faith: I will briefly deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher it, becauſe here is the main ſcruple of our new
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:124528:70"/>modellers of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>To this end, we muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that Logick hath two queſtions. The one is, <hi>An ſit?</hi> Whether the thing queſtioned hath any real exiſtence: The other is, <hi>Quid ſit?</hi> Or <hi>Propter quid ſit?</hi> That is, what the eſſence of it is, or by what cauſe it is?</p>
               <p>In the firſt queſtion, as <hi>Neophites,</hi> we make enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry after the truth of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Faith, by weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the motives: which being conſidered <hi>ab intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeco,</hi> or from the internal principles of them, we finde profoundneſs, even ſurpaſſing the greateſt
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:124528:71"/>jugdments, with ſimplicity, proportioned to the weak, eſt underſtandings, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered with ſanctity, compared to the tenents of all ſects, either of Infidels or Hereticks, wherein they do infinitety exceed them all.</p>
               <p>If we do conſider <hi>ab ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſeco;</hi> that is, by their inſeparable annexed habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liments: we finde perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and inviolable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, delivered from hand to hand, from the very fountain to us, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed ſufficiently by the very Church walls; we find alſo moſt exemplary holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe, who imbrace this faith, which <hi>St. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:124528:71"/>celebrates, in his book intituled of the manners of the Catholick Church: alſo wonderful change of manners in thoſe who are new converts by the ancient, much valued An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical purity, and ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious auſterity of both Sexes, who imbrace He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remitical, Cenobitical, or Anachoretical recluſions: alſo the gallowes adorned with the blood of ſo many illuſtrous martyrs, as in our Country, where ſo many learned men expoſe themſelves to all cruelties, for the good of others, and voluntarily under go igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious death daily for the confirmation of others:
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:124528:72"/>Laſtly, the working of miracles, that is, ſuch wonders which either in ſubſtance tranſcend all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as to reſtore ſight to them that are born blinde, or raiſe the dead, and the like, or in the manner as to cure diſeaſes, without applying cauſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Out of theſe and the reſt of the motives, by reaſon we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to be able to make a firm judgment; firſt, of the manifeſt credibility of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick miſteries: inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that we clearly ſee, that it is more reaſon to be matriculated into the Church, then into any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sect. This ſtep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made and digeſted, by
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:124528:72"/>further penetrating, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſively all the motives, we find the conjunction of them all to be impoſſible to the whole latitude of nature: which a wiſe man weighing, in compariſon to the continual mutation, and viciſſitude of all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral cauſes, will be able to <hi>demonſtrate</hi> the Catholick to be ſupernatural, and abſolutely true, becauſe reavealed and inſpired by God, which is the laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of our Faith; wherein as you ſee reaſon conducteth us in our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, to the full reſult; that is, to the formal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our Faith; which is, <hi>God revealing,</hi> where
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:124528:73"/>we ſtick not for our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: but for the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, wherein Chriſtian Faith is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated. It is true, that the firſt Chriſtians, to whom theſe revelations were immediately made, were prophets: but to the eſpecial aſſiſtance of God in our aſſenting to theſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural truths already revealed, doth not make prophets, which is an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a different nature from formal revelation, as ſchool-men at large de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate in the tract of Faith, and it is evident in it ſelf; wherein Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> ſeems to have erred.</p>
               <p>Hitherto we uſe reaſon
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:124528:73"/>in the diſquiſition of the truth of Faith ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the queſtion, <hi>An ſit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the other queſtion, called, <hi>Quid ſit?</hi> Or by what means, or cauſes is it? Which amongſt Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians is the nobler queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In this we proceed not by doubtfully enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the truth of objects of Faith, or of their real exiſtence, which is diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the State of our Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophitiſm; but all fluctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ancy and doubt depoſed, touching the truth of them; wherein our Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians boggle, for they ſtick ſtill at <hi>An ſit.</hi> But our learned men proceed to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:124528:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:124528:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:124528:75"/>the other queſtion, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to underſtand the truths, ſpeculating the eſſences and natures of each of them, and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alternal connexion of them each to other, which is the proper Sphear of a divine, or ſchool-man, for his own and others ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. There are the bounds of our reaſon, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening to attain and to preſerve already attained Faith; wherein as is clear, reaſon is the ſervant, not miſtris.</p>
               <p>But on the contrary, ye give no limits to reaſon: but as in the progreſs, or ſearch, ſo in the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Faith, ye ſtill ſtick
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:124528:75"/>moſt to your reaſon, and therefore ye doubt or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, what ye underſtand not, for ye perſwade your ſelves, that the myſteries neceſſary to be beleeved, ought to be <hi>per ſe nota</hi> clear in their very terms; inſomuch that every one of you brag your abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute comprehenſion of them. And hence it comes, that the Socinians call in queſtion, if not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely deny the diety of the Son, and of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt; hence with the Pelagians, they reduce Chriſts death to example of our imitation onely, not to be the price of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; hence gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:124528:76"/>they profeſs with <hi>Chillingworth</hi> and others, whom I could name; that holy Scriptures are to be underſtood according to each mans ſmall reach of reaſon, as if nothing were contained in them, what is not commenſurated to our underſtanding, and therefore needs not any ſupernatural aide from God; which Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well confutes, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. <hi>n.</hi> 28. Yet he ſaith, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the <hi>City</hi> to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret Scriptures, at leaſt in all ſuch things, which he will pleaſe to call juridical, or Philoſophical, which have far too great latitude in his ſenſe. For purely
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:124528:76"/>ſupernatural, he ſpeaks more reaſon, then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of theſe new ones: from whom hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded contempt of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, and Doctors; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every one of the moſt inferiour Laytie of theſe Enthuſiaſts by their impetuous imaginary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, and private ſpirit: or what is the ſame, their particular ratiocination, though moſt groundleſs, are ſupreme and infallible Maſters and Doctors to themſelves. Neither do they beleeve any thing to be Divine, which flowes not from the ſenſleſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuoſity of their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, without any
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:124528:77"/>reſpect to higher conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
               <p>Yes truly, thoſe who are eſteemed the wiſer ſort, following <hi>Socinas,</hi> ſtick in the ſame puddle; expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holy Scriptures and all myſteries of our holy Faith; not according to the univerſal reaſon of the Church, delivered by the hands of the ancients to us as Catholicks do, but by their private ſpirits, or by the conduct of their private reaſon: A thing ridiculous to conceive, that the profoundneſs of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian miſteries, ſhould not exceed the ſhallow reach of our reaſon. Which er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror is the Source of all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonancies,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:124528:77"/>and inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies amongſt them: which even by intrinſecal &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequence, muſt needs cauſe a perpetual flux, or iſſuing out of changes of concluſions of Faith: for the effect can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be more noble then the cauſe.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick tenents muſt by a great neceſſity be always conſtant: becauſe they depend not upon our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly changable reaſons, or ratiocination, but upon the unvariable word of God, revealed and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the Church.</p>
               <p>The ſum of all is: that the verity of a Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:124528:78"/>concluſion, is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by the verity of human reaſon: the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Chriſtian reaſon is proved by the verity of ancient faith; indeed one verity may be diverſe, but never adverſe to another. Neither doth Divine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict human; but often ſurmounteth it: and therefore it is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by the ſparks of our ſcanted reaſon, but it is ſetched from elſe where, <hi>Ask thy Father, &amp;c.</hi> This is a ſafe way, in which there is no danger to be daſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the rocks of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, according to that of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Epicietus,</hi> teaching how
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:124528:78"/>Hereticks, &amp; Schiſmaticks are to be treated with. There is no better way, and indeed it is alone ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to anſwer them: Thoſe things not to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxall, which our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers have not taught us. This is plea enough againſt all pretences, in the judgment of <hi>Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us:</hi> let therefore Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and they that bear the name of Chriſt, be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed; if leaving the fountain of antiquity, from whence all ſound doctrin floweth, to follow certain ſmall rivolets, full of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and foolery, ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under a precious ſhew of reaſon: which from
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:124528:79"/>whence they had their Source and beginning none for certain know. We Catholicks therefore adhere to the holy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels and ancient Fathers in the firſt place after the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures: neither dare we accuſe them of foolery, a Chriſtian minde will hurdly permit them to be raſhly and preſumptuouſly defamed: But theſe men, and others of the ſome tribe, who make the glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering of their reaſons the rules of Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: eaſily reject them. It is a wonder rather, that they do not with their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percilious ſpectacles clime up the heavens; and there
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:124528:79"/>with the <hi>Albumazar, Aicaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Maſſaeius,</hi> and infinite other Aſtrologers, ſeek out the verity of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions: and one while, for the conjunction of <hi>Saturne</hi> with the <hi>Sun</hi> adhere to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſmes;</hi> another while, for the conjuction of <hi>Mars</hi> with <hi>Jupiter,</hi> promote the Chaldaick Sect; if with <hi>Venus,</hi> the Mahumetical; if with <hi>Mercarie,</hi> the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. So by ſome little ſhew of reaſon drawn: from the heavens, they may change their religion (as for the moſt part, they are wont to do) ſeveral times of the year, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſeveral domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the planets, or
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:124528:80"/>certainly every year accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the annual domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: or if this ſeems to much aerial, they may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Succeſſory government of thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligences, which they call <hi>Seconds,</hi> appoint the ſtations, retrogradations, and cadences of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſects and religions, as ſome not without applauſe of ſuch lunitick perſons have unhappily enough attempted: as eſpecially ſome attribute the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Luthers</hi> ſect, to the new lunary inteligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces then 1517. underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the worlds govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And <hi>Ticho Brahe</hi> affirms that thoſe ſects,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:124528:80"/>which indeed are derived from mens brain-ſick fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, may be found out in the heavens, both in their riſings and fallings: Of which this preſent age adminiſtreth change e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
               <p>The truth is; <hi>Judas</hi> the Apoſtle toucheth theſe home: whatſoever they do not know they blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme; whatſoever like bruit beaſts, they know they are corrupted in. They are indeed ſo ſwoln in their imaginations, that breaking they corrupt themſelves and others</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:124528:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> A digreſſion against Mr. <hi>Hales,</hi> the ſuppoſed Author of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Schiſm: And a farther proof of Schiſm in <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Mr. <hi>HALES,</hi> who is ſaid, and ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be Author of the Treatiſe of Schiſm; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that Schirm may be ſpread over all the parts of the Church, and ſo the whole be infected; in which caſe Schiſm cannot be imputed to one place
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:124528:81"/>more then to another: and this may peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be affirmed of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puration of <hi>England</hi> from other Churches, as it was touching the ancient cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating of Eaſter; wherein alſo, a how Schiſm is riſon, for aching not neceſſary; yea, (ſaith he) in a matter ridiculous. If I ſhould bring the general Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> condemning and ſeparating from theſe <hi>Quarta-decimans,</hi> he would deride it; he accuſeth all the ancients of fooliſhneſs in this matter: Thus he ſporteth and trifleth in myſteries of faith, to root out all faith out of the mindes of the faithful.</p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:124528:82"/>
               <p>I deny firſt what he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verreth; that the Weſt and Eaſt were at variance: that is to ſay, that that Schiſm did invade, the whole Church, and cleave her into two parts for the matter of Eaſter, but that ſome conſiderable part did raiſe ſtirs in the Eaſt, yea, in the Weſt alſo, is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt amongſt hiſtorians; this cauſe of diviſion in a late work <hi>de conſilijs</hi> made in latine by a Country man of ours, is laid open to the very root.</p>
               <p>But to peruſe a little more the grounds of his miſtakes in this impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant point of Schiſm, we muſt alwayes remember
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:124528:82"/>what before we noted; that Schiſm is not proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſeperation for Hereſie or Error in point of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, or Faith; but in point of diſobedience, which is not a trivial mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as all common-wealths will eaſily conceive, being that nerve, upon which all order de pends; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Quarta-decimans</hi> being rebellious to the mandatory decree of <hi>Nice,</hi> all Catholicks had reaſon to decline their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>I know <hi>Theodoret,</hi> in <hi>l.</hi> 1. c. 13. of his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, and other learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men with <hi>St. Athanaſius</hi> in his tract of Synods, do
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:124528:83"/>eſteem that the queſtion of Eaſter was not defined, as a point of faith, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be obſerved as a cuſtome derived from the Apoſtles; and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this, they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that the Councel va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth the form of ſpeech in a migitatory way, from the accuſtomary ſtile in declaring points of faith, ſaying: <hi>Viſum eſt ut omnes obtemper arent;</hi> in queſtion of faith, they did not write <hi>viſum eſt.</hi> But <hi>credit Eccleſia Catholica:</hi> Thus the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church beleeved <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore, if his undervaluing the cauſe of this Schiſm, grew from this groſs miſpriſon of the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:124528:83"/>ſtate of the controverſie, he ſhould do well to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume his better diligence in examining it.</p>
               <p>He might with greater appearance, have brought that folemn word combat touching perſon &amp; hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis, betwixt the eaſtern &amp; weſtern Churches: which great <hi>Athaenaſius</hi> more clearly opened and cloſed up again. Many conteſted ignorantly after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of thoſe who fight with their eyes ſhut, and beat the air. Some held three hypoſtaſis, other but one in the diety: from whence great contentions aroſe: But as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> relates: <hi>When we asked out
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:124528:84"/>of what reaſon they ſpeak theſe things, or why all do uſe three kinde of words? They made anſwer, that they beleeved in the Trinity,</hi> &amp;c. Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving therefore this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation and excuſe, we examined thoſe who aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that there was but one hypoſtaſis, &amp;c. <hi>Who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that they underſtood</hi> Hypoſtaſis, that is perſon, to be all one with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is eſſence, &amp;c. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all by the grace of God, after this interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the words did approve of the beſt and exacteſt rules of faith, which the Fathers of <hi>Nice</hi> had inſtituted.</p>
               <p>Some indeed for their
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:124528:84"/>material errors, did deny communion; but as yet there was no formal Schiſm betwixt the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but perticular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, perhaps it might have grown to a greater head, had not great <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> interpoſed or rather had not Chriſt Jeſus hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred it.</p>
               <p>But among us, the altar of diviſion, is erected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the altar of union with Chriſt: out of which it is impious to celebrate Chriſts miſteries: the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is not of words, but ſubſtance, not againſt the letter, but the life and ſenſe of the holy Sorip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. If theſe things be
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:124528:85"/>trifles; why do you ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate your ſelves? Why do you puniſh Prieſts with death, who are followers and miniſters of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion? Againſt all meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and clemency of the ancients. To conclude; Why have you built a new altar, framed the ſtones of ſcandal and diviſion? At leaſtwiſe, ye have broken down and demoliſhed all the old ones? inſomuch, that ye abhor the very name of tar, as theſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times in your d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtick, yet fiery contention in pulpits and pamphlets about 12. years paſt, ſuſſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently teſtifie: to what end is all this, if the difference
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:124528:85"/>betwixt you and us be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but about a Cock and Bull?</p>
               <p>And that the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, affirmeth it to be lawful to communicate with the Arians, and Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychians, Neſtorians, Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Sabeſſians; becauſe it is not certain, that theſe invented their hereſies out of malice: but it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe concerning the Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees, Valentineans, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians, and Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans; becauſe it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to all, that they taught theſe blaſphemies againſt their own judgements.</p>
               <p>I wonder at this aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from a perſon of his eminency: for abſtracting
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:124528:86"/>from the intention of the former, againſt whom not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding there was ſufficient preſumption, as among the ancients is clearer then the Sun, no leſs then againſt the other; but to grant, I ſay, what is not to be granted, what is that to me, whether they have vomitted out their hereſie to the eternal deſtruction of ſouls, with a formal or onely inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretive intention to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive? As long as I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with them, and leave the truth taught from the beginning, and delivered by the hands of the Fathers unto poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. We muſt look here
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:124528:86"/>upon the hereſie, not the minde or intention of the heretick: that not this, damneth the ſouls of thoſe that communicate or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinatiouſly adhere unto it: as <hi>St. Auguſt.</hi> often argueth in the the errors of <hi>St. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> and the Donatiſts, whom this Author alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rideth. But to come home to him: Who knoweth not but that <hi>Luther</hi> againſt his own judgement began this Schiſm? Who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth framed it out of a fained and adulterate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? Who of us doth not know, that Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi> out of no Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but politick ends, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:124528:87"/>the Schiſm into Hereſie? If therefore for this reaſon, Communon with ſuch are not lawfull, (as he affirmed of the laſt Apoſtates) neither cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly is it lawful here.</p>
               <p>Neither will it help them what the others are wont to object; that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> did enjoy a priviledg, which they call <hi>Cyprium;</hi> indeed <hi>Tomakas, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>drenas,</hi> and many were that the Biſhop of <hi>Cyyprus,</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared exempt from the jur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſdiction of the Biſhop of <hi>Antioch:</hi> The conſequenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt not be drawn to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in reſpect of the Sea of Rome, except an expreſs priviledge can be ſheweth,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:124528:87"/>which hither to was never dreamed of; yea, beſides other common titles of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; the caſe of the Bulgars, may, and ought to be drawn unto us, to wit, for the title of converſion, as the deciſion of the cauſe is in the law.</p>
               <p>Indeed there is extant a decree in <hi>Con. Conſta.</hi> c. 2. That Biſhops muſt not confound and intermingle their Churches, but ſtand to the appointed rules and their certain limits are affigned to the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs. In the firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Epheſus</hi> alſo, it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, that no Biſhop in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the province of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which was not firſt
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:124528:88"/>and from the beginning under his, or his anceſtors juriſdiction: Hence it was, that the cauſe of the Church of <hi>Cyprus</hi> was heard, which the Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> would have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto him: but it was judged that that yoak ſhould be ſhaken off upon another title.</p>
               <p>The Country was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted unto Chriſt by <hi>St. Barnabe,</hi> whoſe relicks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found there with <hi>St. Mathew</hi>'s Goſpel upon his breſt, written by <hi>St. Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be;</hi> this gave occaſion to commence a ſute of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption, that they might enjoy the priviledge of a Metropolitan: which was
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:124528:88"/>granted; ſo that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they were onely ſubject to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> The general Councel it ſelf in the eighth Canon ſpeaks home of it, and checks the Biſhop of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och,</hi> for having tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Eccleſiaſtical and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical rules in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: namely, becauſe he did ordain in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> which was alwayes an act of juriſdiction, to which he had no juſt title, becauſe theſe Churches were never put under him, as appears in the Councel. What ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude hath this caſe with the known ſubjection of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Rome;</hi> known I ſay, and acknowledged;
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:124528:89"/>even by our lawes ever from the converſion of the Country under <hi>St. Gregory.</hi> All lawful mutations of Provinces, which were ever made, as long as the Church was in her full power, had to this effect the eſpecial authority of ſome general Councel. So in the Councel of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> many dioceſes, and ſome whole Provinces were made ſubject to that Patriarch, which before were ſubject to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and the Primate of <hi>Trace.</hi> So in the Councel: of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi> exchange of Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces was decreed between the Patriarch of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> and in the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:124528:89"/>firſt general Councel, the ſea of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Patriarchate; and the refore the Fathers took ſome Provinces from the Patriarchate of <hi>Antioch,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from <hi>Alexandria:</hi> And in the foreſaid exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the Cyprians could not ſhake off the authority of <hi>Antioch,</hi> till the decree was produced of the Councel of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> Much loſs this Iland ought to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> by reaſon of the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile of converſion, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, but long before the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of <hi>St. Auſtin,</hi> under Pope <hi>Elutherius,</hi> by <hi>Elva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and <hi>Meduinus,</hi> Prieſts,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:124528:90"/>being requeſted thereunto by King <hi>Lucius, Anno Dom.</hi> 179. Whileſt it was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt by the Brittans, in which primitive faith, it remained immaculate and uncorrupted (except the queſtion of <hi>Paſcha,</hi> in which it was corrupted by Picts, and Scots) indeed they reſiſted <hi>St. Auſtin,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they thought he ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the Saxons, who had expelled them by force out of the kingdom, and becauſe they had an Arch-Biſhop of their own of <hi>Leganceſtriae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe other things, which the Author ſo often cited of the Treatiſe of Schiſm, mentioned (for he proves
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:124528:90"/>nothing:) concerning the nullity of power, or of all ſuperiority of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans as they are ſuch; ſo that no obedience but ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple reverence, is due to our betters, except that which may ariſe, by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain convention amongſt men, not by right.</p>
               <p>This Tenet indeed, if made good would make all Schiſm impoſſible; all ſuperiority ridiculous, and arbitrary but it is far from Chriſtian verity, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scripture it ſelf, and all common ſenſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. And truly, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the ſame Author ſaith, in, and for the cauſe of the Donatiſts; if it hath
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:124528:91"/>any favour, he doth not onely accuſe <hi>St. Auguſtine,</hi> but the whole Church of fooliſhneſs, and malice; and all the Prophecies of the fignes of the Church, upon which <hi>St. Auguſtine,</hi> &amp; before him <hi>Optatus, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom,</hi> and all Biſhops and Doctors rely, out of the old and new law, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and the Acts of the Apoſtles; all which in them this man derideth: what he ſpeaketh of the uſe of Images, he ſimply af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, as the reſt; but is ſo far from proving any thing, that he doth not ſo much as attempt it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it a thing worthy my inſiſting upon, ſince
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:124528:91"/>every Abodary Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſt, makes it obvious to children. Yet Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> will force me afterward to joyn iſſue with him in it.</p>
               <p>In fine: The Treatiſe of Schiſm ſpeaketh many things which ſeem diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to Chriſtian faith, which he barely propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, or rather ſuppoſeth, out of which falſe ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he doth falſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that there is no Schiſm in the Church; but as <hi>Ariſtotle Pol.</hi> l. 2. c. 4 right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admoniſheth: Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions indeed may be made, as every one plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, but not impoſſible ones.</p>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:124528:92"/>
               <p>Neither is it of more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what <hi>Antonius de Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis l.</hi> 4. and others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend; that it was not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the Africans to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to <hi>Rome,</hi> according to the 22. Canon. <hi>Concil. Mele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi> And in like manner <hi>England</hi> was not bound to recur thither, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; but juſtly provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for its own right, whileſt it withdrew it ſelf from the Roman yoak; as the African Church living in the diſtrict of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archate, procured to it ſelf the ſame eaſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt I ſay; that <hi>Africa</hi> did in no wiſe withdraw it ſelf from the obedience of the Sea of <hi>Rome.</hi> I add
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:124528:92"/>moreover, neither did it deny the right of appeals, but in certain caſes &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain perſons; to wit, ſimple Clearks, which did appeal thither without obſerving any order of law, which the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> did &amp; doth at this day condemn; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe read <hi>St. Auguſtine, ep:</hi> 162. Omitting others, who expreſly affirms the right of appeals to the Sea of <hi>Rome.</hi> So the pretended Canon, made by the conſent of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſheweth no other thing; but in no wiſe, as I ſaid, did it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw it ſelf from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the Sea of <hi>Rome.</hi> Neither is there
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:124528:93"/>the leaſt ſhew of it, but of the clean contrary in the reciprocal letters of that Councel to the Pope, and of him to them; as may be ſeen in the body of the Epiſtle of <hi>St. Auguſtine,</hi> it would be tedious to learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Readers if I ſhould write them out, they will more eaſily recur to the place cited.</p>
               <p>I add further, worthy to be noted: If the right of appeals had been there abrogated, yet it concludes not, that the juriſdiction of the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> over them, was anulled: except any ſhould be ſo ſenceleſs, as to imagine that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Pretorian
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:124528:93"/>Court, were not ſubject to the Roman Emperors, becauſe their authority deſerved to be advanced to ſuch a height, that it was not lawful to appeal from them, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>F. de offic. Pref. Praet</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am not ignorant, that ſome Grecians as <hi>Nilus</hi> contend, that the right of appeals which the Seat of <hi>Rome</hi> hath (for he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth that) in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the other Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, doth not convince that Seat to have juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction over them.</p>
               <p>Becauſe by the ſame reaſon the conſtant Inopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan having by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> Can. 9.
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:124528:94"/>the ſame power over their Metropolitans, doth not exexciſe juriſdiction over them.</p>
               <p>I anſwer; That be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth only the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to have the ſame power over the general Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, which he hath over other Biſhops who are ordained by authority de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore concludes, that the Pope cannot <hi>trouble</hi> their ordinary government, which is true.</p>
               <p>This therefore confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what hitherto hath been ſaid; and maketh good, that <hi>England</hi> by all law remains ſubject to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> under pain of Rebellion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:124528:94"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> Proteſtants have made this Schiſm.</head>
               <p>IT is clearer then noon day, that not Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, but Proteſtants have made this Schiſm, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the Church: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, when in any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth governed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame Prince, or Soveraignty, and by the ſame lawes a few men withdraw themſelves from the obedience of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and increaſing in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, they begin to ſet up their conventicles, make
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:124528:95"/>lawes; and the reſt of the body remaining in the ancient manner of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, under their own Soveraign power, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim a war: It is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, not the Body of the Common wealth which ſtill perſevereth in the ſame ſtate; but theſe few men receding from the Body with their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, have made the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and blown up the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: In the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner have Proteſtants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved themſelves towards Catholicks, before the ſcandal of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. or rather of <hi>Luther,</hi> the whole Catholick Church conſiſting of divers King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:124528:95"/>in which <hi>England</hi> is compriſed, did obey di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Princes; were gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by divers civil Lawes and Statutes, yet they worſhiped God but in one faith, and in one ſacrifice, were ſanctified with the ſame Sacraments, did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Rector, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Then aroſe <hi>Luther, Henry</hi> the eighth, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> &amp;c. Who brake Communion with the whole world, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſacrifice of the whole Church, and the greater part of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the holy rites, to revolt from the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> all the Church
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:124528:96"/>beſides perſevering in the ſame unity, worſhip and obedience, which before it did profeſs.</p>
               <p>Who therefore doth not ſee, that they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from the Church, and erected altar againſt altar (if they have any) and have been the ſole Authors of the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unity of the Church: I add, that Schiſm is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a dividing of an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted body, or a ſeparation of a part from the whole preexiſtent, or fore being: now the Catholick Church was an united body, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtent before <hi>Luther,</hi> from which the Proteſtants might go out, and divide
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:124528:96"/>themſelves; but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſants ſeeing they were no where, could make no body from whence the Catholicks could recede; therefore the Proteſtants could onely firſt make the diviſion, and blow up the Rebellion.</p>
               <p>The other often heard phantaſtick refuge, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with when theſe are bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with novelty, like men in a deſperate nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage, they catch at any broken reed; namely, that they always were of us, and amongſt us, and ſo continued till they were caſt out of us.</p>
               <p>To the firſt part I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; That till <hi>Henry</hi> the
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:124528:97"/>eighth they were indeed amongſt us; that is, all their progenitors were Catholicks; this every man in the teſtaments and records of each family can witneſs, for the world till then knew no other: all publick profeſſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was that.</p>
               <p>To fly to interiours, that is to ſay, that they were in their hearts, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, were to recur to divination: which were more then childiſh in things of this nature, when all exteriour acts contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict any ſuch dreams; and yet to this clear <hi>non-ſenſe</hi> they are put, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to aſſert their
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:124528:97"/>Church for above a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeers, to have been inviſible, as it is underſtood under the notion of a body ſeparated from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; you will ſee it in <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker</hi> in his 2. and 3. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie <hi>p.</hi> 479. <hi>Field</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how deſtructive this Tenent would be, in his 10. C. Accounts it fooliſh, to ſay that a Church ſhould not have always known profeſſors; and <hi>White</hi> in his defence of the way <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 790. Saith poſitively, that Religion is falſe, if it cannot ſhew a continual deſcent; yet, <hi>p.</hi> 520. he is not aſhamed to ſay, that their Church hath had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed always ſucceſſion, but
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:124528:98"/>not viſible; ſo that being preſſed to ſhew the real ſvcceſſion, he is conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to recur to this ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous divination of mens interiour Proteſtancie, though they profeſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe.</p>
               <p>Which contradictory ſhiſt of their's, were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to deſtroy their pretended Church. <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux</hi> in his ninth Leſſon of the inviſibility of the Church, after many braggs comes to this poor refuge, and beats about like a man deſperate, to ſave his caſe upon a broken reed, or diſtracted ſentence in any obſolute or forlorn Author.</p>
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:124528:98"/>
               <p>But sa I noted: They will ſay that they divided not the Church, neither did they recede from it, but were caſt out of it by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication of the Pope; and therefore not they, but the Pope was the Author of this diviſion: but this helpeth them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. For to omit; that excommunication is a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment which is inflicted upon ſuch, as go out of the Church, not ſo much caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out of the Church, as depriving them of the participation of common benefits thereof: to omit this it is notoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known to all that <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, <hi>Luther,</hi> and
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:124528:99"/>Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> went out of the Church before they were excommunicated, as being condemned by their own proper judgments: and ſo they ſeparated themſelves, and before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excommunication, made the Schiſm, in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment whereof they were excommunicated: touching <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, it is manifeſt, that he was excommunicated for his diſobedience and contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy in grievous crimes: and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by and by when ſhe had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the Crown upon her, ſhe ſeeing the Pope diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult in declaring her law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful title unto it, not for
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:124528:99"/>her religion (for then ſhe had not changed it) but for illegitemacy, even ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Acts of our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments under her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, broke off all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church of God: So <hi>Camden</hi> in <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> The Engliſh alſo compiled a book of Canons wherein they alſo confeſs, they went out of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a frivolous thing, that they pretend they went not out, but were driven out of the Church.</p>
               <p>They may perchance reply, that they were as amongſt us, ſo of us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this diviſion, and ſo are yet; becauſe it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:124528:100"/>to incorporate any body into the true Church of Chriſt, if he beleeveth the Creed of the Apoſtles as here Proteſtants do.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer: Firſt, that in ſome caſes this may be enough, yes even to beleeve Jeſus Chriſt to be the Son of God is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, as in the caſe of the Eunuch and ſuch like, that is an implicite faith, may ſuffice till other neceſſary truths are ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded: For the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel had and hath a time of growth in every new Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. In theſe and ſuch like caſes it is ſufficient, not to miſ beleeve former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly other truths, to conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:124528:100"/>a man a member of Chirſt's Church.</p>
               <p>I anſwer: Secondly, That the ſame God who truſted his Church with this, hath as well entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her with all other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary truths, The Holy Ghoſt hath taught her <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem veritatem</hi> all and every neceſſary truth, as our bleſſed Saviour promiſed: which ſhe <hi>pro re nata,</hi> as hereſies pullulate, declares to her children, that they may be able to avoid the danger of ſwallowing ſtones inſteed of bread.</p>
               <p>Theſe truths, thus by ſupreme power propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the faithful, they are obliged to receive by
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:124528:101"/>obeying their Prelats, who have a charge over their ſouls, according to that of the Apoſtle <hi>obedite praepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitis veſtris, &amp;c.</hi> Hence the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a moſt fundamental truth, Chriſt Jeſus to be <hi>Deum de Deo et conſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem Patri, &amp;c.</hi> to be God of God conſubſtantial to the Father, &amp;c. which is not in the Apoſtles Creed: neither is it there that the Holy Ghoſt is God, nor the Fathers of <hi>Nice</hi> did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that great truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe yet hereſies touched not that point: as <hi>St. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſile,</hi> and <hi>St. Gregory Nariane</hi> teach; yet I beleeve, that every true Chriſtian will
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:124528:101"/>eſteem it neceſſary to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve theſe truths; it is eaſie to deſcend to many more particulars, which all Chriſtians admit to be neceſſary, though not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Apoſtles Creed, as concerning the Sacraments of Baptiſm, and the Euchariſt, &amp;c. The Church hath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore always from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to this day belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and practiſed this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme obliging power in matters of faith and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: and upon the ſame ground hath always e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed ſuch hereticks, in a damnable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who have not as well beleeved or adhered to
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:124528:102"/>her propoſals in faith in one ſubject as in another, and as well to the end of the world as in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times</p>
               <p>But they ſay that the burden of Chriſtian religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be greater, then of the Jewes, and intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if all are obliged to every declared truth in the Church, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. that his yoak is ſweet, and his burden is light.</p>
               <p>This is eaſily anſwered, in order to the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſtians, whoſe implicite faith in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructures is ſufficient, according to the generally
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:124528:102"/>taught and received do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of Doctors. Paſtors indeed and Doctors have higher obligations to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to give an account of their faith, which obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is much alleviated by the Synopſes of Faith, which the Church clearly and yet very contractedly propounds to keep them principally from miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the holy my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of our faith. This is the weightieſt objection which I finde in Mr. <hi>Hobb's,</hi> beſides thoſe which I ſhall preſently touch.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>St. Chryſoſtome</hi> in his 10. homily upon <hi>St. Mathew</hi> in the perſon of Chriſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of Mr. <hi>Hobbs, Nolite
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:124528:103"/>de difficultate conqueri, queſi qui doctrinam meam moleſtam eſſe dicatis:</hi> we muſt not ſay Chriſt's doctrin is troubleſome, leaſt with the Capharnaits, we be committed <hi>abire retro,</hi> to be put in the back ſide of Chriſt's book.</p>
               <p>Surely <hi>St. Auguſt.</hi> found Chriſtian religion in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poſture, then Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> would have it in his 5. Chapter to <hi>Voluſian.</hi> Where he ſaith that <hi>Tanta eſt Chriſtianarum profunditas literarum, ut in eis quotidie proficerem, ſi eas ſolas ab in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eunte pueritia uſque ad de ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitam ſenectutem, maximo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, ſumma ſtudio, meliori in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genio, conarer addiſcere,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:124528:103"/>He experienced the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Chriſtianity, far to tranſcend the ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue: he eſteemed his whole life though it were imployed in nothing elſe, not to ſuffice for a perfect underſtanding of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profundities; ſurely they were not ſo vulgar as Mr. <hi>Hebbs</hi> would have them.</p>
               <p>There was among the Jewes a difference in points of faith, ſome were <hi>ut adirces</hi> as the foundation of the reſt, the denying whereof would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the whole law: others as <hi>rami</hi> branches where the danger was not ſo conſiderable. Theſe <hi>R.
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:124528:104"/>Menaſſieth</hi> in the beginning of his Treatiſe of the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the world decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.</p>
               <p>So in Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome things are <hi>ſimply</hi> neceſſary, without which heaven is not to be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; as the faith of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which our ſchool-men place <hi>ſub neceſſitate me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dij,</hi> that is as abſolutely neceſſary: of which ſort there are not ſo many.</p>
               <p>Other things are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary onely <hi>ex ſuppoſitione,</hi> that is upon ſuppoſition that they are made known to us, or ſufficiently decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: then there is <hi>neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas praecepti,</hi> a command to imbrace them, and ſurely
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:124528:104"/>this is no great burden.</p>
               <p>I will alſo touch that impertinent objection of the Socinians; that the Church of Chriſt is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of all Chriſtians, or of all who beleeve in Chriſt, and not of any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect body of them, and conſequently there are no hereticks to be declared ſo by any ſentence of the Church; but onely thoſe are hereticks who by their own judgement are ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. That is, ſuch who againſt their own judgment do reſiſt known truths, not ſuch who by a councel or body of men are declared ſuch. This to beleevers
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:124528:105"/>is eaſily made evident to be impious.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That Chriſt hath a Church, he hath ſaid it, that he alſo hath inſtructed her with a regitive power he hath alſo ſaid it, and ſaid both together in theſe words, <hi>Dic Eccleſiae;</hi> and therefore addeth to ſuch as obey not her decrees, <hi>ſi eam non audierit ſit tibi tanquam Ethnicus et publicanus,</hi> we muſt complain to the Church for emergencies, and ſhe hath power to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate if we obey not.</p>
               <p>If this be true as it is in other crimes and cauſes, it will eaſily conclude in the chiefeſt crime of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:124528:105"/>elſe we muſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly ſay that Chriſt hath made proviſion for the leſſer difficulties, and not for greater, which is to condemn his omniſcience or providence.</p>
               <p>Again, this regitive power is confirmed in the acts and attributes to the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Spiritus San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus vos conſtituit Epiſcopes regere Eccleſiam Dei.</hi> Of this the new Teſtament in doctrin and practiſe is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant.</p>
               <p>Further, that the Church hath power to declare he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, is evident, beſides the immediate conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of it out of Chriſts words related, out of the
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:124528:106"/>doctrin and practiſe of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>They did teach how, or did inſtitute the manner, <hi>poſt ſecundam monitionem</hi> to declare and excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate for hereſie, they alſo did declare <hi>de facto</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, as is evident in almoſt all their Epiſtles and the Apocalipſs, and did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid all commerce with them, which is to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, which they did for their falſe and ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tenents or innovations in faith, as is clear in the texts; whence it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth firſt, that the Church hath this power, as firſt <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> for teaching it lawful to buy the Holy
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:124528:106"/>Ghoſt. Secondly, the Jewiſh Chriſtians, who taught it lawful to uſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental circumciſion under Chriſt, were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by <hi>St. John,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Whence it followes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly; that the Church is not a body of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but of all who do joyn in the unity and integrity of faith; elſe if declared by the Church to be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, they are no longer of her, becauſe by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity derived by Chriſt, they are caſt out of her. Their own interior guilt will ſerve to accuſe them in the Court of God in Heaven; but it is the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:124528:107"/>act of the Church upon their pertinacy which condemneth them in Earth; and this ſentence is confirmed in Heaven, <hi>Quaecunque alligaveritis &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> in his 18. Chapter <hi>n.</hi> 2. requires two vertues neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; Faith, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Faith hath no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther latitude in her acts then to beleeve Jeſus to be Chriſt, <hi>n.</hi> 5, 6. and ſo forward.</p>
               <p>Beſides internal faith, he ſaith that there is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily required a <hi>profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of many other articles, which ſummarily are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted &amp; compacted into that we call the Creed.
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:124528:107"/>As he had touched before, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. <hi>n.</hi> 21. and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward more fully in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations to the number 6. Yet he eſteemed not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians bound to beleeve, but to profeſs theſe if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. This ſeems a bull in Chriſtianity to be bound to profeſs in matter of belief, what I am not bound to beleeve: yet this he aſſerts <hi>Chap.</hi> 18. <hi>n.</hi> 6. neceſſary to ſalvation out of title of obedience. That is, I am bound to profeſs, that I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, what I am not bound to beleeve; I propound this to Mr. <hi>Hobb's</hi> ſecond thoughts, he bog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles much upon it in his
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:124528:108"/>Annotations, utters evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent contradictions, and yet he comes not off. Nay he ſaith <hi>ch.</hi> 18. <hi>n.</hi> 14. that it is enough if one endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to beleeve them, though he doth not, but he muſt profeſs them when he is required.</p>
               <p>Is not this to put a lie upon himſelf, for a man to profeſs to beleeve what he doth not beleeve? Nay, is not this to put a lie upon Chriſtianity? He adds, that he cannot exclude ſuch from heaven, who internally do not aſſent to articles declared by the Church, if they do not contradict, but being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, will grant them,
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:124528:108"/>(this laſt particle of exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal acknowledgement is more modeſt, then I have yet found in any of our Country-men) though it cannot be digeſted by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable man, that I may profeſs what I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve.</p>
               <p>The texts of Scripture whereby he proves the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal belief of Jeſus to be Chriſt, ſufficient to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are very weak in principles of Chriſtianity. For beſides, whom I have named already, who were condemned by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles for beleeving falſe doctrin: There were alſo the Nicolaitans in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalips, Chap. 2. Who
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:124528:109"/>following <hi>Nicolas</hi> one of the firſt ſeven Deacons, who beleeving in Chriſt, yet taught it lawful to commit fornication, and to eat meat offered to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, were heavily threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from God by <hi>St. John;</hi> ſo alſo thoſe hereticks, whom <hi>St. John</hi> ſignifieth by <hi>Jeſabel,</hi> who taught it lawful to do the ſame. Neither will it help Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> his Tenet. That <hi>Jeſabel</hi> is ſaid to teach, that is, not onely beleeve eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally thoſe errors; for thoſe of the Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> were threatned becauſe they did <hi>beleeve</hi> thoſe falſe doctrins, and the Apoſtle <hi>St. Paul</hi> in his
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:124528:109"/>firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy v.</hi> 3. uſeth this word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, where he giveth to <hi>Timothy</hi> power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce to hereticks not to teach otherwiſe then they had been taught, neither is his diſcourſe of faith in Chriſt, but of ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, as the courſe of the text ſheweth, and in it he forbids any to <hi>beleeve</hi> them. In fine, it is clear in all Eccleſiaſtical monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as well Hiſtorical as Doctrinal; that from the Apoſtles to this day, not onely ſuch who deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Jeſus to be Chriſt, who were properly Infidels or Apoſtates, but who belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not any other article
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:124528:110"/>propounded by the Church univerſal as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, were eſteemed hereticks, and in ſtate of damnation.</p>
               <p>All the texts for the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency to beleeve in Chriſt in order to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, except in caſes afore mentioned, are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of all things which belong to faith in him, in which is comprehended his Church inſtructing in all neceſſaries, or elſe the faith in Chriſt nakedly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> would exclude all thoſe benefits, which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve to be obtained by him. It is true, that in particular caſes (as I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted)
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:124528:110"/>an implicite faith of many of them might ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, as in the Thief, where he had not time for other inſtruction or profeſſion; yet, it is evident he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the whole, when he cryed <hi>Memento Mei,</hi> &amp;c. But theſe extraordinary caſes are nothing to the ordinary courſe of Gods providence, which we one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch: And thus the Church of God from, and with the Apoſtles always underſtood this matter, and accordingly in her Councels ſquared her pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe. But as I ſaid before of the Thief, ſo of the Eunuch, and the two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand converted by <hi>St. Peter;</hi>
                  <pb n="210" facs="tcp:124528:111"/>it is evident, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved in the ſubſtance of the whole Creed, for the very children of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> knew the main doctrins which Chriſt taught, as appeared in the publick proceſs againſt him cryed up and down the ſtreets; and therefore theſe belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in him, beleeved in all which he had taught; which will come home to the Creed at leaſt.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> will tell you in the upſhot, that the points now in controverſy, for the moſt part concern onely contention for a worldly Kingdom, gain, or victory in point of wit, where he expounds them
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:124528:111"/>after his own guſt and names, onely ſuch, which may more plauſibly be thought to have ſuch ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, omitting the chiefeſt in agitation about the Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which concern the principal end and effect of our redemption; as free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, and juſtification, he rejects as Philoſophical. Thus the high miſteries of Chriſtian Faith, by a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian are made ſubjects of diviſion, or rather of delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or colluſion. <hi>Herod</hi> was afraid of Chriſt, becauſe he was jealous that his aim would be to get his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, this jealouſie was the cauſe of much innocent
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:124528:112"/>blood-ſhed. I hope Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> hath no ſuch deſign, in ſtirring up this old falſe plea againſt Chriſtianity: for Chriſt hath aſſured all men that <hi>his Kingdom is not of this world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there hath been always ſubordination in Church judicatures is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by <hi>St. Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and every where in holy Writ, which hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been continued, even in external government, as all Hiſtories ſhew, and yet not prejudicial but auxilliary to temporal power. But for any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies is point of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral power, challenged by the Church I know
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:124528:112"/>none foraſmuch as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth faith. Yet Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> ſeems to deſire, though with much violence, to draw even hearing confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and interpreting ſcriptures to his new <hi>Euto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> as belonging to civil Magiſtracy.</p>
               <p>There is yet another ſhift, wherein as the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>mentitur ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas ſibi,</hi> they frame an imaginary pillar of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; ſaying, that though the firſt openers of this breach were Schiſmaticks, yet they having been born in this Church, are not guilty of it. As when a Kingdom is unjuſtly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, yet it may be juſtly
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:124528:113"/>poſſeſſed by future heirs. This I have weighed and anſwered before: yet to the ſimilitude I particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwer; that there is no parity at all to plead preſcription againſt God, becauſe in ſome caſes there may be among men; elſe all Hereticks, and Turks, may more forcibly plead this right then they, if naked countenance of poſſeſſion can give title. I might here queſtion the ſuppoſition it ſelf, for even in temporals, the civil and Canon law require more time for preſcription in order to ſome perſons, then to others: as for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary perſons, ten yeers;
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:124528:113"/>in ſome forty, in ſome an hundred.</p>
               <p>Again, there is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, not onely in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but the things poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as Eccleſiaſtical, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more time then ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: and there is always required a quiet poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to begin the count of yeers, that there may be <hi>titulus probabilis.</hi> The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe then the true lords are thought vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, or implicitely to yeeld their right: And thence begins the title in the unjuſt poſſeſſors; namely, when the ancient lord, being able, ceaſeth to chalenge any right. But as I ſay, to let all this paſs;
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:124528:114"/>the diſparity from man to God is manifeſtly clear, and therefore admits of no conſequence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> Proteſtants have made the Schiſm with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cauſe or ground.</head>
               <p>THE often cited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Doctor, in the Treatiſe of Schiſm wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth; that Schiſm doth not always make the leſſer part culpable which recedeth, or is driven out from the
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:124528:114"/>reſt of the common-weale, or body of the Church, but the compulſive cauſ is here chiefly to be looked upon, and not always the ſmall number of the receding perſons: therefore the Proteſtants ſay; it is true, that they made the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Catholick Church, but did it rightly and worthily, for the intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable errors and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doctrins which then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected the whole Church: and therefore they follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the command of the voice of God, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18. <hi>Go out of her my people, that ye be not made partakers of her ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The damnable doctrins
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:124528:115"/>are by themſelves reduced cheifly to Idolatry, the other differences they conceive may be more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſwallowed: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this were a capital one, if true, and it were no leſs ſtrange; that the Church of Rome which reduced this Iſland and moſt part of the two worlds from Idolatry, ſhould it ſelf knowingly teach or practiſe it, and no leſs ſtrange, that theſe few men after ſo many yeers ſhould ſee theſe groſs abominations, which ſuch an infinity of learned men in ſo long time, nor yet can finde or judge to be ſo. Idolatry according
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:124528:115"/>to Divines is taken for a religions worſhip due to God, and given to any creature. In this all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians agree.</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the holy Sacrament of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt,</hi> giveth indeed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip out of infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible ſuppoſition, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe Elements, is the body and blood of Chriſt, accompanied with his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity: they do not give it to the accidents, no not to the body and blood of Chriſt properly, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely, but to the Divinity; ſo preciſe they are in the Divine worſhip; whence it is clear, that they do not direct their worſhip to a
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:124528:116"/>creature, but to God; and though they cannot but involve in their adoration his preſence under the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of bread and wine, yet do not formally termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate their act to this <hi>preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiallity</hi> of Chriſt in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, which is but a relative, a very extrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal accident, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently not capable to terminate a divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; whence we ſee the proper object is Chriſt, who certainly is exiſtent; and therefore in this they are not miſtaken, even in all ſectaries opinions; and therefore there can be no Idolatry, even though Chriſt had not that new
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:124528:116"/>ubication under the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of bread and wine, that being the acceſſory, not the principal which they aim at, for they adae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quately direct their action to Chriſt preſent, not to the <hi>preſence</hi> it ſelf abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting from Chriſt, ſo that their miſtake would be in a circumſtance, not in a ſubſtance; and therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven admitting that impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſuppoſition, yet there would be no Idolatry.</p>
               <p>The other particle is their worſhip of Images; which in no wayes can be called Idolatry. Firſt, becauſe they do not at all teach Divine worſhip to be due to them, as is clear
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:124528:117"/>in the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> and as all knowing Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants will confeſs: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, many great School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do not hold any wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip at all to be preciſely directed to them, it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fient, reverently to retain them, and by them to be raiſed up in devotion to the thing repreſented by them; as by a picture of Chriſt to be called upon to remember Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As they think it is deduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble out of the Councel of <hi>Trent:</hi> Out of which it is evident that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is injuriouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed of Idoltary.</p>
               <p>And here I wonder much at Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> in his
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:124528:117"/>book <hi>De Cive,</hi> who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſingularly deſerving in moral and ſocratical Philoſophy, would ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily preoipitate his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in points of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>He ſaith in his Chapter 15. <hi>n.</hi> 18. That if the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to worſhip God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a picture, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were-bound to do it: In his Annotations upon the ſame place, he calls himſelf in queſtion for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilogies in this particular, for in <hi>n.</hi> 14. He had taught that to worſhip God by a picture, or any Image, were to limit God to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain terme, which were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:124528:118"/>the law of nature touching Gods worſhip, which ſurely deſtroys the firſt poſition.</p>
               <p>To the anſwer of this, he ſaith, the offence would be in the commanders, not in the obeyers, by reaſon they worſhip him thus up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on compulſion. He adds, that if God ſhould ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally forbid to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the uſe of an image, that then ſuch a command could not be obeyed, as it is in the decalogue, were expreſly Idolatry is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited. Afterwards in the 16. Chapter <hi>n.</hi> 10. trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; he ſaith, that to worſhip God by an Image
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:124528:118"/>is againſt the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as he ſaid in the 15. <hi>c. n.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſeem to be ſtrangely inconſiſtent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. Firſt, the power which he ſaith, <hi>n.</hi> 17. in the 5. Chap. To be transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Magiſtracy from the people in determining Gods worſhip, he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that it ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to reaſon.</p>
               <p>He confeſſeth alſo in his Annotation cited; that to worſhip God under an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage were againſt reaſon, becauſe Idolatry; not onely becauſe now God hath forbidden it (as he ſaith) but in it ſelf, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe as he ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:124528:119"/>it were to preſcribe a term to his infinity, and conſequently to make God to be finite.</p>
               <p>Whence it followes; firſt, that though Idolatry is againſt the light of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and therefore intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecally wicked, yet know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly I might do it, if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by a Magiſtrate, ſo that an inferior power, namely, a power derived from my ſelf, can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me that which is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely prohibited by the higheſt power, as is that of nature, and I am bound to obey it with neglect of the other though ſupreme, yet the Magiſtrate cannot command it, but againſt
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:124528:119"/>reaſon; and therefore ſuch a command cannot be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatory, becauſe in his 5. Chapter and <hi>n.</hi> 17. reaſon is the limit of that power. Are not theſe inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtences?</p>
               <p>Again he ſaith, that moral compulſion (for a command is no more) would render an act of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry lawful, becauſe it would exempt it from I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry. This is deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of all religion, and truly of reaſon, in all Schools of Philoſophy. where <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thicks, and all others teach; that we muſt loſe our lives for vertue it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Again he ſaith, that if
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:124528:120"/>God make a poſitive law to the contrary, as he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth he hath, that then I may not obey the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer command of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, how this is recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable to his former te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, that worſhiping God by Images is againſt the law of nature, and yet one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unlawful if commanded by Magiſtracy, becauſe in the Decalogue or poſitive law it is again forbidden; I know not, for ſurely this law is inferior to that of nature, according to all men, and reaſon it ſelf being the law of nature, is drawn from the very nature of the thing it ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="229" facs="tcp:124528:120"/>
               <p>That God hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Idolatry I doubt not in his firſt Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but whether to worſhip God by the uſe of Images is there forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den? Or whether it be Idolatry, would deſerve Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> his greater dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to prove it</p>
               <p>For ſurely to ſay that it were a confinement of his Infinity, would be as far from a proof as it is from truth, clear in the light of reaſon and evidently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scripture: where we are taught to glorifie God in and by his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, according to the 18. <hi>Pſalm. Caeli enarrant glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Dei,</hi> &amp;c. The heavens
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:124528:121"/>ſpeak Gods glory. How they do ſpeak it? they can declare no more then they are, according to Mr. <hi>Hobbs;</hi> and therefore onely things finite, which is to confine God againſt the drift of the <hi>Pſalms:</hi> Philoſophy, and Scriptures teach us to finde God by his creatures, as <hi>St. Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Rom.</hi> 20. remits us to the creatures. <hi>Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilia à conſtitutione mundi per ea quae facta ſunt intellecta conſpiciuntur,</hi> our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of God is from theſe viſible things: nay, it is the onely natural way we have, from the effect to finde the firſt cauſe; and not from the firſt cauſe the effect, and all things
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:124528:121"/>without his confinement. So by pictures we aſcend to what is repreſented, not tying our ſelves to the manner in our worſhip of God under that repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: In the purſuit we relinquiſh the manner, and going forward with our diſcourſe we find, and with our devotions follow the Infinity of Gods goodneſs. All repreſentatives are eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially inferior to the Prototypes by many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, yet ſafely conduct us to the knowledge of them without abaſing their natures to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages. So here and all acts of acknowledgment of God, in, and by his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:124528:122"/>for we know the effect cannot equalize the firſt cauſe eſpecially, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in nature, nor in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of exiſtence; and therefore we conclude, Gods ſupreme eſſence and goodneſs to tranſcend all we ſee; &amp; in the like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we eaſily aſcend by the uſe of pictures, neither can we do otherwiſe if we uſe our reaſon; ſo that there is no danger of Gods confinement, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no Idolatry.</p>
               <p>I remember that <hi>Caſſian</hi> in his Collations tells us of a poor ignorant Monk; who out of error, had fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to himſelf in his nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row imagination a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:124528:122"/>of Gods being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and could very hardly be brought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain higher thoughts of Gods ſpiritual eſſence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unwillng to relinquiſh his Phantaſtically ill fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Image of God.</p>
               <p>We are much beholding to Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> who is ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Chriſtians dulneſs, that leaſt by their Images, they ſhould conceive God to be finite or corporal; with this poor Monk, he would remove all pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturs, though God himſelf; not ſo careful as Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> hath been pleaſed to talk and walk with <hi>Adam,</hi> which are acts of a corporal and finite creature, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:124528:123"/>to make reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, as if he had appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in corporal ſhape, as to <hi>Moſes,</hi> perchance to <hi>Jacob</hi> and others; nay, even the Son of God appearing in our poor nature, all which would draw us into errors, if God had not by his Prophets, Apoſtles, and daily by his Church, and even by reaſon taught us the right uſe of ſuch paſſages, and to know, that thoſe ſenſible repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives were onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductives to God himſelf, as we teach Students by em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems to conceive things more remote from their preſent capacity. All which will warrant our uſe of
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:124528:123"/>Images, yet without Gods confinement and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently without Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
               <p>Neither would this, if true, any way excuſe them from ſacrilegious Schiſm, except all were compelled to Idolatry. <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, there can be no juſt neceſſity to cut off unity <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>Cont Ep. Parm. c.</hi> 2. and as he elſewhere <hi>Ep.</hi> 166. <hi>Our Heavenly Maſter hath ſo much admoniſhed us to take heed of this; That he would make the common people ſecure even of evil ſuperiors, that not for them the chair of ſaving do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin ſhould be deſtroyed.</hi> Therefore the chair ought not to be forſaken, much
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:124528:124"/>leſs deſtroyed for the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the Preſidents. O how <hi>St. Cyprian</hi> doth purge that poiſon of theirs to the quick! <hi>Epiſt.</hi> l. 3. <hi>Ep</hi> 2. If there be ſeen dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel to be in the Church, our faith and charity ought not to be hindred there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that becauſe we ſee darnel to be in the Church, we therefore leave the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtle in the ſecond <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> 2. ſaith: In a great houſe there are not onely veſſels of gold and of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but alſo of wood and of earth; and certain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed unto honour; but certain alſo unto contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but it is onely lawful
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:124528:124"/>for God, who hath a rod of iron, to break the earthen veſſels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let not any one aſſume to himſelf what the Father alone hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to his Son, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is (ſaith he) a proud obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy and ſacrilegious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, which wicked fury aſſumeth to it ſelf. Let our Country men think ſadly of this.</p>
               <p>It is objected to me, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth force her Proſelites to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve falſhoods, pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly under <hi>Anathema</hi> in the Councel of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer; That if we ſhould make an impoſſible ſuppoſition againſt all the promiſes of Chriſt, that
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:124528:125"/>the Church ſhould in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary points teach er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors: yet even in that caſe, every child of the Church muſt exteriorly carry himſelf quiet, and not make commotions; for that were to ſeek a cure, worſe then the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, as in the like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible ſuppoſition our Country-man <hi>Waldenſis l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 27. teaches. <hi>Non perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram inſilire debet.</hi> He muſt not leap againſt the Churches face in rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Neither is he bound to beleeve an untruth; nor yet is one in danger to incur the cenſure: For the Church cannot reach the minde; onely God in
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:124528:125"/>a juſt ſentence confirming her act reaches home, which cannot be in this caſe, for he ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm an injuſtice. Whence it followeth, that no man is or can be compelled <hi>to beleeve untruths;</hi> but onely not to make Schiſm: which by divine law is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. And therefore <hi>St. Auguſtines</hi> rule is ſtill true: There cannot be no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of cutting off the Church unity, no not in ſuppoſition that ſhe ſhould command great errors.</p>
               <p>But you will not object, that if the articles com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Church are in themſelves true; yet if I cannot perceive
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:124528:126"/>their truth, after all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence uſed to that end, it were hypocriſie in me; and therefore unlawful to adhere to that Church, I conceive though falſly, teacheth and commandeth falſe doctrins, and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary practiſes upon thoſe grounds.</p>
               <p>This truly is moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly objected by ſome, but without all Solidity.</p>
               <p>For ſurely Chriſtians are obliged by the law of God and reaſon to depoſe their own falſe judgments, in obedience to God &amp; his Church, elſe this will open a gap to all itching ears (of whom we are premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed) to introduce each
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:124528:126"/>man his fancy, and prefer it before the wholeſome doctrins of Chriſt deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Church.</p>
               <p>Neither is it difficult for man, though learned to depoſe his own judgment, eſpecially in order to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal actions, for it is dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done by all ſorts of ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate conſciences, who do mangre their own rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, direct themſelves by the authority of ſuch, whom they know to be more learned then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hobbbs</hi> Chap. 15. and n. 13. ſaith, <hi>unuſquiſque ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem privatam, rationi totius civitatis ſubmittere poteſt.</hi> Here he labours to lay the
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:124528:127"/>grounds of the derivation of power in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth to determine what belongs to matters of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which he faith that the people have transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Magiſtrate. He proves it as he faith evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently (I examine it not being pertinent to my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne) His proof is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every man in his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate worſhip, before the City was made, was to be guided by his private rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> therfore he might ſubmit to the publick rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. If this be true in point of reaſon, as Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> much contendeth in order to the civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate;
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:124528:127"/>how much more will this be concluded in reſpect of ſpiritual Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, to whom this power is conveyed, not from the people, but from God, as Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty teacheth. Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> goeth far beyond this, for he will have each one to be obedient to his <hi>Civil</hi> Church even in things clearly unlawful; as he tells us in his 15. <hi>Chap. num.</hi> 18. and elſewhere fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently. Thus they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn Chriſtian obedience in things moſt congtuous to Chriſtian reaſon, and yet authoriſe their own tribunals contrary to faith and reaſon.</p>
               <pb n="244" facs="tcp:124528:128"/>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> ſaith, <hi>n.</hi> 17. That except the power of determining Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, were in the law of nature tranſlated to the City or Magiſtracy, that there would be infinite ſects, diviſions, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently confuſions in it; and therefore he ſaith conſequently enough, that every man muſt ſubmit to it.</p>
               <p>The antecedent I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not: for the law of nature is a law declared according even to him, <hi>n.</hi> 3. <hi>Pertacita rectae rationis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctamina,</hi> by the ſecret ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions of right reaſon, in which he differs not from <hi>Cicero, Lex naturae eſt ipſa
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:124528:128"/>ratio ſumma, inſita in natura quae jubét ea quae faeienda ſunt prohibetque contraria,</hi> &amp;c. It is not ſo much declared by reaſon, as it is reaſon it ſelf in the higheſt accepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeated in nature, and it is therefore called <hi>Lex na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> becauſe nature, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a certain common vertue, which impels all men to a general proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of good, &amp; avoydance of evil: whence they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not will any thing under the pure notion of evil: In brief, the Law or light of nature radically is a power in the ſoul univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally commanding the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of good and declinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of evil anſwerable to
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:124528:129"/>the firſt principles of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: And therefore ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rigidly, the ſoul in her creation is not ſo purely <hi>tabula raſa,</hi> a bare table; according to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and his followers, <hi>Plato</hi> and his whole ſchool, ſhe is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with univerſal prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, which are called <hi>primae Conceptiones</hi> unreſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able principles, which have no other proofs then the true apprehenſion of the terms or extremes u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited: and therefore are <hi>primò verae,</hi> as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, theſe are the firſt truths in which men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not differ in uſe of reaſon; for otherwiſe if they ſhould fail in theſe, it were
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:124528:129"/>in vain to expect any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent diſcourſes in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructures, but as their diſcourſes would enlarge, ſo would their errors: out of theſe, nature frames her commands univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which is the Law of nature taken formally.</p>
               <p>Whence it follows, that in this matter of greateſt concernment to humane nature: Namely, <hi>the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God;</hi> there needs no tranſlation of power from each particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the City, or whole body of men, becauſe it is as intimately connatural to each, as to all, to know what the law of nature dictates by the conſtant
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:124528:130"/>and <hi>ſecret ſuggeſtions of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> what is to be done, and what is to be avoided, as <hi>Cicero</hi> tells us; whence principally comes, that we call <hi>Syndereſis,</hi> or check of Conſcience, elſe it is not a law of nature, but ſome ſuperſtructure, improperly called natures law, which inſeperably is infuſed into the ſoul to all, who have a ſoul not hindred in her opperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But herein many erre, who confound the <hi>hypotheſes</hi> with the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples whence they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted; that is, remoter concluſions with the firſt, which are immediate, and ſerve as principles to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <pb n="249" facs="tcp:124528:130"/>
               <p>The Law, or light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures therefore immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dictates, that God is to be worſhiped, and none can be ignorant of it, that know the ſignification of the terms: neither can they be ignorant, that Gods worſhip muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the beſt manner. Thus far <hi>Cicero</hi> his <hi>Summa ratio,</hi> pure reaſon convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, men cannot diſagree in this; for as <hi>Cicoro</hi> notes, <hi>non opinione ſed natura conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum eſt jus.</hi> This depends not on opinion which is always ambiguous, but is a law as conſtant and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>But becauſe our natural
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:124528:131"/>knowledge of God is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted only from his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (for the objects of our underſtanding in this preſent condition of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the ſoul with the body, are onely mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial or ſenſible natures de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from our ſenſes) hence our reaſon cannot reach to know the manner of Gods worſhip, becauſe that onely is beſt which is pleaſing to him, note <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe,</hi> that is pleaſing to him, which we judge to be the beſt; though out of this miſtake each nation proceeding, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtanding (as we ſay) in their own light, differed from each other, and
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:124528:131"/>every one from truth, in determining Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <p>To ſay therefore as Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> often inculcateth, that every particular man muſt ſubmit to the whole body for determination of this, ſeems to be as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent a doctrin, as to oblige every blind man to have an inqueſt of blind men to determine what colour any things were of, to whoſe blind judgment every man ſhould ſubmit; though as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tells us, <hi>Caeaus non judicat de coloribus.</hi> The thing were wholy out of their Sphere.</p>
               <p>The determination therefore of the manner
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:124528:132"/>of divine worſhip, can onely be had from God, becauſe none can know his will but himſelf. For as Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> rightly teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>n.</hi> 14. <hi>c.</hi> 15. Gods will is not to be thought <hi>ſimilis noſtrae,</hi> like to ours, but it is to be ſuppoſed to have onely ſome Analogy with ours <hi>quod condipere non poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> which our underſtand can not reach to. Which is alſo <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s, <hi>Averroes,</hi> and the beſt Philoſophers doctrin.</p>
               <p>Whence it follows, that none can know what man nor of worſhip inmoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, &amp; conſe quently what is beſt. Theſe who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſcend our ſphere,
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:124528:132"/>and therefore Chriſtian Divivines moſt reaſonably hold it neceſſary to have ſupernaturally revealed truthes communicated to man-kinde to direct them in Gods worſhip; and ſurely, it were as high and pecoaminous preſumption in any, to offer to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate this, as the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Babels Tower, of which nothing could be expected but eternal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. Whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that never any wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip pleaſed God, which was not inſpired by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, no not in the ſtate of nature.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> muſt therefore retract his injuriouſly
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:124528:133"/>traſlated power to his Common-wealth, and teach his Diſciples to ſeek this knowledge from God, even under the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. As now Catholicks obſerve in all worſhip ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to the Divinity, eſpecially directed in all theſe ſupernaturals by the Church, from which they receive Gods orders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> indeed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth the force of an argument drawn from authority to be very eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable, even in ſchools; and therefore we may adhere to ſo great authority, as the Church even in reaſon.</p>
               <p>But thoſe, who cannot
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:124528:133"/>overcome their own tenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reaſons by overpoiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them with ſo great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as the Church, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly muſt either be mad, that is, hurt in their fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, as I have obſerved ſome, though otherwiſe able to make unbroken diſcourſes, in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of leſs concernment, which is eaſily poſſible, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Philoſophy, or elſe God for other ſins blindeth their underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, as he did <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s; which obſtacle they muſt labour to remove, that they may learn to obey God in his Church, elſe their condition will be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way moſt miſerable,
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:124528:134"/>if they obey not for want of Chriſtian humility they are in evident danger of hell, if they do obey they are in danger, becauſe they do againſt Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; but the remedy of this is at hand, if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh their own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not by ſatisfying, which they pretend they cannot do, but by cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivating to a ſure Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p>Certainly, wicked fury hath made and increaſed this Schiſm: for granting, which is my ſecond an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the former obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; that when unity cannot be kept without detriment of eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:124528:134"/>it may, and ought to be broken without ſin; but when by the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of unity no detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſalvation is incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that if this alſo may be obtained by perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering in unity, then at leaſt there ſhall be no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful cauſe to break unity, and thoſe who break it, do incur certain damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ſacrilegious Schiſm: But now Proteſtants re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in union with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould have ſuffered no detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but had been in a certain way to arrive unto it. As we have ſhewed before, by their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:124528:135"/>that Catholicks perſevering in the ſame unity may attain unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: wherefore it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly followeth that they without any cauſe went out of the Church (wherein they might have been ſaved) and caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their followers into the ſtate of damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: according to that of <hi>St. Auguſtine, De unit. Eccl.</hi> c. 19. <hi>None come unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and life everlaſting ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he hath Chriſt for his head; and none can have Chriſt for his head, except he he in his body, which is the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, which is chiefly to be pondered, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:124528:135"/>to be repeated, thoſe damnable doctrins (as they call them) taught in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ought to have been declared by a general Councel, and not by themſelves, who are the leaſt, if any part of the Church. Otherwiſe, if it ſhould be lawful for every one to accuſe the Church his mother of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, and to leave her without any other diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the cauſe, a gate ſhould be open to all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies; &amp; the Church of God would be trodden under foot, yea all Chriſtianity fall to ruine; this hath been the plea of all ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, which they thought
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:124528:136"/>ſufficiently proved, if one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>accuſing</hi> of error be <hi>proving:</hi> as in the cauſe of <hi>England,</hi> D. <hi>Bilſon</hi> and <hi>Covell,</hi> teach the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Synods in theſe things, the firſt part <hi>p.</hi> 374. the other <hi>p.</hi> 110.</p>
               <p>And that which ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther replied, firſt that <hi>England</hi> might ſufficiently judge of hereſies, newly brought in, ſeeing it is matter of fact, to wit, whether this, or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doctrin came down from our Fathers Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, &amp;c. or whether it were heard of but ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday, or the day before? for this even children may perceive.</p>
               <pb n="261" facs="tcp:124528:136"/>
               <p>The ſecond point alſo, which he not onely by mouth, but by pen (now frequent in other hands) ſo much urged, ſaying, that it is not needful to call a general Councel, ſince by your confeſſions, as <hi>Creſſy, fol.</hi> 443. ſeemeth to inſinuate, that there is no infallable power in them: A doctrin which I was glad to finde amongſt you, yet I wondred at it, being already repugnant to what I had read in your former authors, as D. <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton,</hi> and D. <hi>Stratford</hi> of the Church, and of late in a book made by a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man of ours in Latine, called <hi>Syſtema Fidei: Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi>'s
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:124528:137"/>words are theſe: <hi>No man will endeavour to oblige them further then</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve an obliging authority in the Catholick Church, let is be limitted and confined as ſtraitly, and with as many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes as any Catholick, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed any reſonable man ſhall think good.</hi> I ſay according to this power of defining, and eſtabliſhing faith, it is to no purpoſe to call a general Councel to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare hereſies, when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ignorant fellow can do as much in order to the verity of declaring, though perhaps not in order to the <hi>coercive</hi> manner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring; yea, in the very power it ſelf, for aſmuch
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:124528:137"/>as according to this poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Creſſy,</hi> the power of the Church in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar may be reſtrained by any ſilly fellow, &amp;c. Thus far this Author.</p>
               <p>To theſe I anſwer; For aſmuch as concerneth mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact every nation may witneſs, what they have recived, but they cannot make infallable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment of matters of Faith without the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme judgment of the whole Church, in whoſe onely mouth there can be no errors: which is our principal queſtion. Many things are conveyed to poſterity, which are not matters of Faith, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:124528:138"/>not of truth: this the Church onely ſuerly determines.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of <hi>Greſſy,</hi> I anſwer, that his words, though ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry harſh, yet in my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they may receive a more favourable gloſs, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on connexion with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of his diſcourſe. He doth indeed to much even ſuſpiciouſly ſavour of his old friendſhip, with that vertiginous and fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhy Apoſtata <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> a man whom few exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples have paralel'd in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten turning religion. But <hi>Creſſy</hi> wrote this book in Neophitiſm, not being yet fully inſtructed in the
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:124528:138"/>myſteries of our holy faith, as <hi>St. Hierome</hi> noteth of <hi>Arnobius.</hi> which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is more excuſable in him, though he ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his not throughly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted conceits, hardly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ndugh conſiſtent with the verities of the Catholick faith. I do not beleeve that his intention was, ſo ſoon to play the maſter in teaching what he had not perfectly learned, which had been too prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this whole books <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to give the Hiſtory or gradation of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, how he did reach from one degree to another and how he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth the ſence of our
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:124528:139"/>doctrin, and Doctors, in his paſſage: wherein (as I ſaid) it is no wonder, if being a Neophite, he ſhould boggle in his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of explication, as his expreſſion ſeemeth to do in this; but where he now is, he will better and more fully inform himſelf; and I doubt not but wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie thoſe paſſages which ſavour of miſtakes.</p>
               <p>Neither doth it avail much, though many here ſtumble at theſe, and other of his paſſages; for <hi>St. Hier:</hi> ſaith, <hi>ep.</hi> 76. <hi>I think Origen to be read, So ſometimes for application, as Tertullian, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatus, Apollinaris, Creſſy, and many more Eccleſiaſtical wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:124528:139"/>both Greek and Latin, that we may chooſe what is good in them and avoid the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> There are ſome very good things in that book, though intermixt with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſages more harſh as he ſeems to expreſs them, which a prudent reader may pick out and diſcern to his profit.</p>
               <p>It remaineth therefore firm and certain, that our Country men are bound under the pain of Schiſm and rebellion to reunite themſelves unto the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as King <hi>James</hi> of famous Memory calls her, in his firſt ſpeech to the Parliament) at leaſt wiſe
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:124528:140"/>until a general Councel he convocated, where their cauſe may be heard and decided, which indeed is virtually already done to their hands in the caſe of <hi>Germany:</hi> Wherein the proverb is true that one egg is not more like to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other then theſe in the main point of Schiſm, though differing from themſelves and others in points of Doctrin.</p>
               <p>From what is ſaid we may conclude thus. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever divide the unity of the Church without cauſe are in a damnable ſtate, ſeeing (out of the third Chapter) Schiſm is an enormous crime; but Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:124528:140"/>do divide the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church (out of the 4 and 5 Chapters) and that without cauſe; (Chap. 6.) therefore Proteſtants are in a damnable ſtate. Wherefore (as I ſaid in the beginning) conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the danger of their ſouls they are bound to diſcuſs the cauſes of their revolt; to weigh &amp; ponder the reaſons of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, that they may free themſelves from ſuch a miſerable and dreadful ſtate, return to the Church their mother, and ſo have God for their Father, love and maintain her unity, and ſo be made partakers of her charity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="author_to_the_reader">
               <pb n="270" facs="tcp:124528:141"/>
               <head>An Exhortation of the Author.</head>
               <p>I know that theſe ſenſible objects obvolved and enſnared in the delights of the fleſh, ſtrongly propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed either by actual poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or clear hopes of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, do ſo efficatiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly move the powers of ſouls, drowned in ſordid bodies; that poor man by the weak command of his will is hardly drawn from embracing them; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt ſeek help o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, we muſt fly unto holy prayer, that we be not ſwallowed up in this
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:124528:141"/>gulf of mudd; let more noble objects be propoſed, it is not in our power not to be moved with thoſe things we ſee; let us therefore look with the eyes of Faith upon the objects of eternal felicity promiſed to thoſe who confeſs and follow Chriſt Jeſus, certainly they will concern us, and by Gods mercies through the tryals of patience we ſhall at the length attain unto them.</p>
               <p>Let not therefore that be applied to us, which in times paſt <hi>Seneca. ep.</hi> 116. ſpake of the adverſaries of Stoick Philoſophy: <hi>You promiſe too high-things, you
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:124528:142"/>command too hard things: we are poor creatures and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny all things to our ſelves,</hi> leaſt we hear alſo his anſwer on the Stoicks part: <hi>Our vices becauſe we love them, we defend them, and we had rather excuſe them then leave them: To be unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is the cauſe, not to be able is pretended.</hi> This conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration may eaſily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print a ſerious reflexion in the hearts of Schiſmaticks</p>
               <p>To conclude all, let us hear the great Zealot of Peace thundring out to the Churches of <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Epheſ. 4.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I therefore priſoner in our Lord beſeech you, that you walk worthy of the vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in which you are called, with
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:124528:142"/>all humility and mildneſs; with patience ſupporting one another in charity, careful to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace: One body and one ſpirit, as you are called in one hope of your vocation: One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, One God and Father of all, which is over all, and by all, and in us all. Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:124528:143"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 27. <hi>Line</hi> 11. <hi>Read</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>P.</hi> 83. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>read</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſected. <hi>P.</hi> 87. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>read</hi> prefects. <hi>P.</hi> 96. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>read</hi> impoſtume. <hi>P.</hi> 127. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>read</hi> add faith. <hi>P.</hi> 136. <hi>l.</hi> ult. <hi>dele</hi> to. <hi>P.</hi> 138. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>read</hi> theſe. <hi>P.</hi> 144. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>read</hi> add not. <hi>P.</hi> 174. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>read</hi> Epiſtles. <hi>P.</hi> 195. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>read</hi> radices. <hi>P.</hi> 214. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>read</hi> continuance. <hi>P.</hi> 239. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>dele</hi> not. <hi>P.</hi> 242. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>read</hi> not pertinent.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:124528:143"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
